<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The policy of princes in subjection to the Son. Explained and applied, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Parliament, in Margarets Westminster, on Wednesday the 24th of Sept. 1656. being the day of their publick fast. / By William Jenkyn pastor of Anne Black-Fryers.</title>
            <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87559</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862859</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115037</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240952720</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E888_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202640</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862859</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862859e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115037)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E888[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The policy of princes in subjection to the Son. Explained and applied, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Parliament, in Margarets Westminster, on Wednesday the 24th of Sept. 1656. being the day of their publick fast. / By William Jenkyn pastor of Anne Black-Fryers.</title>
                  <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for John Dallam, and are to be sold at his shop in Shoomakers-Row in Black-Fryers near Carter-lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf bears the order to print.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with imprint giving "Samuel Gellebrand" as publisher.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms II, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Kings and rulers --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115037:1"/>
            <p>The Policy of PRINCES in Subjection to the SON.</p>
            <p>Explained and Applied, IN A SERMON Preached before the RIGHT HONOURABLE THE PARLIAMENT, In <hi>Margarets Westminster,</hi> on Wednesday the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1656.</p>
            <p>Being the Day of their Publick Fast.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM JENKYN</hi> Pastor of <hi>Anne Black-Fryers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>John Dallam,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop in Shoomakers-Row in <hi>Black-Fryers</hi> near Carter-lane. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:115037:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Thursday the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> Sept. 1656.</head>
            <p>ORdered by the Parliament, That the thanks of this House be given unto M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Jenkyn</hi> for his great pains taken in his Sermon preached before this House yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, being a Day appointed for publick Fasting and Humiliation: And that he be desired to Print his Sermon, and that he have the like Priviledge in Printing as hath been formerly allowed in like Cases.</p>
            <p>And that Major <hi>Beake</hi> do give him the thanks of this House accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen. Scobell</hi> Clerk of the Parliament.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115037:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115037:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115037:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE PARLIAMENT OF THE Common-wealth OF England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Ornament</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I endeavoured to set forth my Sermon, was that of <hi>honesty,</hi> not <hi>curiosity,</hi> much less <hi>flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery;</hi> I studied therein more to <hi>profit</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:115037:4"/> than <hi>please</hi> you, rather to shew you a <hi>right</hi> than a <hi>smooth</hi> way, and to shew my self (as <hi>Augustine</hi> speaks) rather <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melius est cum severitate dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, quam cum lenitate deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere.</hi> Aug Ep. 48.</note> to <hi>love with severity, than to deceive with lenity.</hi> After I had chosen my <hi>Text,</hi> I remembred that I was long since certainly informed (pardon me, if I relate what is below so Honourable an Assembly to know) that my dear <note n="*" place="margin">Formerly Preacher at <hi>Sudbury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> where he died about 40 years since.</note> Father (now with God, but once an Eminent servant of Christ in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery) preacht his last Sermon upon this very Text, to which God also di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected my thoughts, <hi>Kiss the Son,</hi> &amp;c. and truly the recalling hereof to my minde, caus'd an <hi>addition</hi> to my desire, that I might so preach to you, as if this Text and Sermon should also both have been my last.</p>
            <p>Some few particulars may possibly here and there be added in printing,
<pb facs="tcp:115037:4"/> which the straits of time alotted both for studying and preaching my Sermon, permitted me not to deliver in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; But upon consulting my memory, my Notes, and the Copy of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Amanuensis,</hi> I am not conscious of my forbearing to print any one sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or any thing, which commonly is called a passage, delivered in preaching of my Sermon.</p>
            <p>I shall onely add, if the things which I preached be <hi>false,</hi> you cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused in commanding so <hi>much</hi> as the printing of them; if they be <hi>true,</hi> you cannot be excused from doing <hi>more,</hi> by adding to your command of <hi>printing</hi> them, your own exemplary <hi>care</hi> in <hi>practising</hi> them: And, as, if they be <hi>false,</hi> I am sure to be summon'd before the <hi>highest</hi> Tribunal for <hi>preaching</hi> them; so if they be <hi>true,</hi> it will be
<pb facs="tcp:115037:5"/> impossible for you to escape the terror and severity of the same Judicatory, should you (which I dare hardly sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) refuse to practise them.</p>
            <p>The great Counsellor guide you in all your consultations to <hi>kils the Son,</hi> as you would avoid his anger. In his work I desire to be your faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full servant</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi>
                  <date>Novemb. 3<hi>
                        <seg rend="sup">d</seg>.</hi> 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>VVilliam Jenkyn.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>Hasty printing hath in part <hi>caused,</hi> but hasty reading will altogether <hi>continue</hi> these <hi>Errata:</hi> Haste not therfore to read, before thou correctest them.</p>
            <p>PAg. 4. lin. 19. read <hi>consideration.</hi> p 6. l. 3. put out <hi>possibly.</hi> and l. 4. r. <hi>who possibly</hi> p. 9. l. 25. r. <hi>it is.</hi> marg. t. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 14. marg. r. <hi>Nieremb.</hi> p. 24. marg. r. <hi>regno.</hi> r. <hi>subjaceret.</hi> p. 29. marg. r. <hi>Nah.</hi> 1. 6. l. 25. put out <hi>either.</hi> and l. 29. r <hi>And also.</hi> p. 37. l. 28. r. <hi>intend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 40. marg. r. <hi>prae.</hi> p. 41. l. 11. r. <hi>severe.</hi> p. 43. l. 4. r. <hi>will at.</hi> l. 5. put out <hi>ll.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115037:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the PARLIAMENT the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>September</hi> 1656.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>. the last Verse.</bibl>
               <q>Kiss the Son lest he be angry.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Finde a threefold interpretation of this second Psalm among Expositors,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The first of such who say that it was wholly intended concerning <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and is simply to be understood of him; and thus the Jews generally hold, though some few expound it of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaphat,</hi> and the vain conspiring of his enemies against him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The second of those who hold that it is simply intended concerning <hi>Christ,</hi> without any respect at all to <hi>David;</hi> and thus the most of the Fathers of old expound it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115037:6"/> 3. The third, of the best, who conceive that it is to be understood in a mixt way, and partly to be interpreted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>David,</hi> but properly and principally touching <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it cannot be understood simply of <hi>David,</hi> 'tis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest, in regard sundry things in this Psalm cannot in any sort belong to him, as in <hi>ver.</hi> 8. where 'tis said, <hi>I will give thee the uttermost parts of the earth for thy possession.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Blessed are all they that put their trust in him.</hi> And the holy Ghost, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 25. <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 33. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1 5. and 5. 5. mentions one intended in the Psalm who is <hi>greater than David</hi> or any earthly King.</p>
            <p>That it should be understood simply of <hi>Christ</hi> without any respect to <hi>David,</hi> I see no cogent reason; in regard that <hi>David</hi> was one who in his life and Office, did <hi>typifie Christ,</hi> and foreshew those things that belong to him, which things like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise seem the more plainly to agree to Christ, by being shadowed out in the type.</p>
            <p>I therefore approve of the <hi>mixt</hi> way of interpreting this Psalm, conceiving that <hi>David</hi> spake it properly and by way of <hi>first intention</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> though not without the type of his own Kingdom, in which he saw the Kingdom of Christ to be shadowed forth (as in the opposition which it had from sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry people, both Jews and others, the enlarging of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and his victories over his enemies, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> and that <hi>David</hi> by occasion of the vain and fruitless endeavours of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies against his Government, prophesieth in this Psalm of the successeles and contemptible undertakings of all those who in any age should oppose Christ and his Church, which was sure to be blest with perpetuall stability.</p>
            <p>The Psalm hath three Parts; The <hi>first</hi> contains a description<note place="margin">First part of the Psalm.</note> of the endeavours of the enemies of <hi>Christ</hi> against his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in the 1, 2, &amp; 3, <hi>Verses.</hi> And</p>
            <p>These endeavours are described, 1. From the Parties using them: Said to be <hi>the heathen,</hi> the <hi>people,</hi> the <hi>Kings of the earth,</hi> the <hi>Rulers.</hi> Words importing not only the <hi>general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of <hi>Christs</hi> enemies, both <hi>Gentiles</hi> and <hi>Israelites,</hi> but their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115037:6"/> great <hi>dignity</hi> and worldly eminency, as being also <hi>Kings and Rulers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The parts of their endeavours, they <hi>rage, imagine,</hi> or meditate; <note n="*" place="margin">Idem verbum legimus de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo, qui adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sabatur Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; ei stricto gladio in via ne tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siret opposuit: stetit Angelus contra Balaam. <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. 32.</note>
               <hi>set themselves</hi> (as in a posture of resistance) <hi>take counsell together.</hi> Noting, First, Fury. Secondly, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry. Thirdly, Resolution. Fourthly, Policy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Parties whom they oppose, <hi>the Lord and his anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> Father and Sonne, served and resisted together.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The scope and end they aime at in this opposition, <hi>viz.</hi> to be exempted from all obedience to Father and Son, whose Laws, these lawless Rebels here express by those odious termes of <hi>bonds and cords,</hi> excusing their unsubmissiveness by asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the Government.</p>
            <p>The <hi>second</hi> part contains a description of the <hi>ineffectualness</hi>
               <note place="margin">2<seg rend="sup">d</seg> part of the Psalm.</note> (and to the undertakers the <hi>perniciousnes)</hi> of those endeavours of the enemies of Christ against him; from the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> to the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg> verse.</p>
            <p>This is proved two waies, 1. By Gods setting himself <hi>against</hi> those enemies, at once both contemning their power, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. and punishing their rebellion, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his shewing himself <hi>for</hi> his Christ, First, In <hi>appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> ver 6, 7. Secondly, <hi>Enlarging</hi> his Kingdom, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. And Thirdly, In <hi>preserving</hi> and stablishing it, promising him success, in the easie and irrecoverable overthrow of all his enemies, <hi>ver.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third</hi> part contains an Exhortation to the greatest of<note place="margin">3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> part of the Psalm.</note> Christs enemies, that had so vainly and so foolishly gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to dash a head of glass against a Piller of brass, and the weak wayes (themselves) against this Rock the <hi>Lord Jesus.</hi> to desist from their undertakings, and to submit to God in Christ: and this Exhortation is laid down in the three last <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> Wherein you have considerable,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>First,</hi> A preparatory Exhortation, <hi>Be wise now therefore,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <hi>O ye Kings, be instructed ye Judges of the earth.</hi> This is preliminary to what he is saying.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The maine Exhortation it self; And that is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> two fold.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115037:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> In relation to God the Father, saith he, <hi>Serve the</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Lord Jehovah,</hi> against whom and his <hi>anointed,</hi> ye have <hi>taken counsell,</hi> ver. 2. <hi>Serve him with fear, rejoyce with trembling.</hi> In joyning both an <hi>act,</hi> and a <hi>suitable manner</hi> of performing it: a due mixture for those that are ready to be hindred by a proud fearlesness from the service of God. <hi>Serve him with fear:</hi> And then</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> You have here the Exhortation in relation to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God <hi>the Son,</hi> out of whom the Father cannot be served (for he that honoureth not the Son, cannot honour the Father.) <hi>Kiss the Son lest he be angry, and ye perish from the way.</hi> In the Text I take notice of three Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st,</hi> Here are the <hi>Parties</hi> unto whom the Exhortation is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> made, the Parties Exhorted, Kiss <hi>ye,</hi> they are the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>the Judges of the earth.</hi> So you have it in the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>ver. Ye Kings, ye Judges of the earth.</hi> q. d. Kiss <hi>ye</hi> him, you that I have advised before to be <hi>wise,</hi> for this is your true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, your true wisdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I here take notice of the <hi>substance</hi> of the Exho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and that is to <hi>Kiss the Son.</hi> Here I observe, 1. The <hi>Object,</hi> and that is the <hi>Son.</hi> And 2. The <hi>Act,</hi> that is <hi>kissing</hi> of him, <hi>Kiss the Son.</hi> And then the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third</hi> part considerable, is the <hi>Argument</hi> by which he <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> doth inforce this Exhortation, <hi>lest he be angry, and ye perish from the way.</hi> Here I note two things; The first is the <hi>cause</hi> of their ruine, if they will refuse subjection to Christ, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>anger</hi> of the <hi>Son.</hi> Secondly, The <hi>manner</hi> of their ruine, it shall be <hi>in the way:</hi> for so <hi>Calvin</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stands the words. And so I conceive we are here to take the meaning of them, <hi>lest ye perish in the way,</hi> in the <hi>midst of</hi> your counsels, lest you be <hi>suddainly</hi> taken away, even when you <hi>cry peace, peace,</hi> before you come to the end of your undertakings, and think you are well and secure. And thus I have given you the Parts of the Text, in these three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations: And now I have broken the words into these <hi>three Parts,</hi> you must give me leave to <hi>knit</hi> them up all three again, together in one Proposition, and it shall be this;</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115037:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Kings and the Judges of the earth must kiss the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Observ.</note>
               <hi>Son if they would avoid his anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You must not be offended with the Doctrine, unless you be offended with the Text; I have in a manner given it you in the very words thereof; and now again I shall <hi>break</hi> the Doctrine into those three parts that I mentioned before; which three having doctrinally explicated and illustrated, we shall come (God willing) to the using, and to the impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it, for our own benefit by application.</p>
            <p>Three Particulars, I say, are here doctrinally to be explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and amplified:</p>
            <p>First, Who are those <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> here called upon, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and Why are <hi>they</hi> exhorted <hi>to kiss the Son</hi> rather than others?</p>
            <p>Secondly, How they may be said to <hi>kiss the Son?</hi> and then <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Why by this same arguing from the <hi>anger of</hi> the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Son, are they put upon this duty of <hi>kissing the Son,</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lyes the force of the Argument? These are the three things that in the doctrinall illustration of this Point I shall (God willing) insist upon; and then in the <hi>second place,</hi> we shall come to the <hi>application</hi> of the whole.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>Who</hi> are those Kings and those Judges that are here <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> exhorted? and why <hi>they</hi> are exhorted? These <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> are the same that are spoken of in the <hi>first verse</hi> of this Psalm, where 'tis said, not only concerning the <hi>Heathens</hi> and the <hi>people,</hi> that they <hi>raged</hi> and <hi>meditated,</hi> (the Heathens <hi>without</hi> the Church, and the people <hi>within,</hi> the <hi>Israelites</hi> as some interpret it,) but that <hi>the Kings of the earth set them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and the Rulers take counsel together:</hi> there it is, <hi>melakim</hi> and <hi>rozenim, Kings</hi> and <hi>Rulers;</hi> here it is, <hi>melakim</hi> and <hi>shopetim, Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges;</hi> but both places intend the same thing. The word <hi>Kings</hi> is (you see) again repeated, and <hi>Judges</hi> here may very fitly answer to that of <hi>Rulers</hi> ver. 2. and by them may be meant, inferior Governors and Rulers, which might be Counsellors to Kings, and preside in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments under Kings: and <hi>to judg</hi> is oft in Scripture taken more largely than to examine and determine causes and cases, even <hi>to rule and govern,</hi> or to be in authority, in which respect
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115037:8"/> the Judges (in that book) are frequently said, so many years to <hi>have judged Israel,</hi> that is, to have ruled and governed them: by Judges then, are meant Rulers under possibly Kings, who are named here <hi>before Judges,</hi> because as 'tis their part to put their Judges upon, and also to quicken them in their duty, so commonly according to the pleasure of the <hi>King,</hi> you shall see in most places the deportment of the <hi>Judges</hi> or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Rulers. To these <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> this exhortation is principally directed, and that for these reasons:</p>
            <p>First, These of all others are <hi>most unwilling</hi> to stoop to Christ. The greatest in place are most hardly brought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the lowest in their own apprehension: <hi>Every knee must bow unto the Lord Jesus,</hi> but the knees of Princes are of all others the stiffest and unwilling to bend, <hi>non facile mansues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt,</hi> 'tis hard to make them pliable to Christs pleasure: and this both in regard of their apprehension of their wisdome and carnall policy, as also of the greatness of their strength and wealth <hi>(their strong Tower</hi> in their own opinion.) Commonly where there's no want there's much wantonness: 'tis true, they have more temptations than others, it is a hard thing to be <hi>full</hi> and not to <hi>kick;</hi> (and certainly they do deserve, in this respect, more our pity than our anger) a great condition, never that I yet heard of, occasioned any mans conversion. <hi>I will get me to the great men</hi> (said <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> Chap. 5. 5.) <hi>and I will speak unto them, but these have altogether broken the yoke and burst the bonds. Who is the Lord</hi> (said potent and proud <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Exod. 5. 2) <hi>that I should obey his voice to let Israel go? I know not the Lord, neither will I let Israel go.</hi> Greatness unsanctified, is but as oyl to nourish the flame of pride and contempt of God: and God to make his people lowly and pliable, often makes them low and poor. Religion seldom flourisheth in the soyl of a rich mans soul: and 'tis our duty not only to be willing to want, but even to pray against that worldly greatness, which may occasion us to deny subjection to Christ: <hi>It is as rare to see a man high and humble, as to see one poor and patient.</hi> There is the first Reason. But then</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115037:8"/>
            <p> Secondly, Unto the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges of the earth</hi> this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Exhortation is directed, to shew the <hi>greatness</hi> of Christs exaltation, intended here in this Psalm. The highest must stoop, and certainly then Christ <hi>himself</hi> is very high. If <hi>every knee must bow to him,</hi> then surely Christ himself is the <hi>King of Kings and the Lord of Lords, and higher than the Kings of the earth,</hi> yea to be worshipped by the <hi>Angels.</hi> Worshipped he must be, by <hi>ministring spirits,</hi> and so he must be by Ministers both of Church and State. How great is he whose subjects are Kings!</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> are here exhorted, because they have <hi>more engagements</hi> lying upon them than others, to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> yeeld obedience. This was the greatness of <hi>Davids</hi> sin, that <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 18.</note> he would lift up the heel against God that had lifted him up into the Throne. It is by Christ that <hi>Kings reign, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces decree justice.</hi> It was <hi>Baashas</hi> sin, as you read 1 <hi>King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8. 15, 16.</note> 16. 2. that when God had <hi>exalted him out of the dust, he would walk in the way of the house of Jeroboam.</hi> God had raised him up to power, and he raiseth himself up to rebellion. God having given unto <hi>Nebuchadnezzar a Kingdom, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5. 18.</note>
               <hi>and glory and honour,</hi> would not endure that he should strut and vaunt it in his great <hi>Babel,</hi> and not take notice of that God that had advanced him. It is all the equity in the world, that they who have more honour <hi>from</hi> God than others <hi>have,</hi> should return more honour <hi>to</hi> God than others <hi>do,</hi> even <hi>return as they have received.</hi> Nothing more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse and unseemly, than for people to obey Kings, and for Kings and Judges to disobey God, and to fight against him with his own weapons.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>These</hi> are here exhorted, because they have <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4,"/>
               <hi>greater opportunities and abilities to do good than other men,</hi> both by precept and example: <hi>Scilicet in vulgus manant exempla regentum,</hi> upon the common people commonly flow the examples of Princes; it is oft their fault that the people are so bad, and either from the imitation of their lives, or obedience to their Laws, that people are so disobedient to Christ: one <hi>Jeroboam</hi> made thousands sin with him. <hi>Ephraim</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hos. 5. 11.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115037:9"/>
               <hi>willingly walked after the commandement.</hi> 'Tis too much for any to be a follower in sin, but none can too much be a leader in holiness. Though Rulers cannot put in security to save any harmless at the day of judgment, for following them in sin, yet seldom go they to hell without mis-led company; And if Religion at the <hi>Barr,</hi> when it is in a holy and a poor <hi>Paul,</hi> make a sinfull <hi>Magistrate</hi> to tremble, certainly Religion in the Throne, or on the <hi>Bench,</hi> will sooner make a <hi>Malefactor</hi> at the <hi>Barr</hi> to tremble. Though it be the holiness which we love not, yet if it be joyned with the power which we fear; though it be the goodness which we despise, yet if it be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the greatness we admire, it will probably have many followers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Because the obedience of <hi>Kings and Rulers</hi> to Christ, shews the <hi>necessity of the subjection of inferiours to him.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Will not God exempt <hi>Kings</hi> from his service? surely then poor ones must stoop. Kings, as <hi>Calvin</hi> saith upon my Text, seem among men, <hi>legibus soluti, &amp; communi ordine exempti,</hi> to be exempted from regular obedience, and to have a dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to live as they list. And if any men in the world have liberty to be and do so, <hi>they</hi> are accounted the men; but you see that these are commanded to stoop, and therefore their <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> must needs become subject unto the Lord Jesus. If God will not indure a proud King in a Throne, yea not a proud Angel in Heaven, certainly then not a proud worm in a dunghill. This for the opening of the first Particular: and that is, who these are that are here exhorted, namely the Kings and the Judges of the earth. I now proceed unto the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second,</hi> and that is the Exhortation <hi>it self.</hi> And there I <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> take notice,</p>
            <p>First of the <hi>Object,</hi> and that is the <hi>Son:</hi> Kiss <hi>the Son.</hi> The word <hi>Bar</hi> here translated <hi>Son,</hi> sometimes in Scripture, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> signifies pure, or clean, <hi>Job.</hi> 14. 4. <hi>Job.</hi> 11. 4. or purity, <note place="margin">Psal. 24. 4. Psal. 73. 1.</note>
               <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. 25. <hi>Psal.</hi> 18. 24. But then it comes from the root <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he purged, or purified.</hi> But it likewise in Scripture very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently signifies a <hi>Son:</hi> Thus it's used <hi>thrice</hi> in one <hi>ver.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115037:9"/> Pro 31. 2. <hi>What my son, and what the son of my womb, and what the Son of my vowes!</hi> and <hi>thrice</hi> in two verses: namely <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>Ezra</hi> the 5<seg rend="sup">th,</seg>
               <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>Zechariah</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>the son of Iddo, Zerobabel</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>the son of Shealtiel, Jeshua</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>the son of Jozadak.</hi> So <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 25. <hi>The form of the fourth is▪ like the Son of God,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] which <hi>fourth,</hi> we may understand to be <hi>Christ:</hi> and its thought by some to note <hi>a chosen, belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
               <note place="margin">Filium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum <hi>Pagn.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>son,</hi> above the rest; the deriving it from [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] that signifies to <hi>chuse,</hi> and gather a thing apart as the chief among many. But <hi>Buxtorf, Pagnine</hi> and others, rather think it to be a <hi>Chaldee</hi> word, answering to the <hi>Hebrew Ben, a son:</hi> and its used in severall Names importing the same: as <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jona, Barnabas, Bartholomew, Bartimaeus.</hi> The word <hi>Bar</hi> then signifieth <hi>son,</hi> (though the 70 render it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vulgar Latin <hi>disciplina,</hi> yet herein are they opposed even by the Papists themselves, <hi>Pagnin, Vatablus, Arias Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus:)</hi> And what <hi>son</hi> can be here meant, but the eternall <hi>Son</hi> of God, the second Person in the glorious Trinity, who is here called <hi>the Son,</hi> by way of peculiar excellency, from whom it is that others <hi>are,</hi> and are <hi>called</hi> the <hi>sons</hi> of God. And very fitly is subjection to the <hi>son</hi> subjoyned to the <hi>ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in the forgoing <hi>verse,</hi> this being the only true and acceptable way of serving the <hi>Father,</hi> who is only <hi>known, worshipt</hi> and <hi>enjoyed</hi> in the <hi>Son.</hi> Whatever wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship is given to the <hi>Father,</hi> is nothing worth, unless it be given through <hi>Christ.</hi> If <hi>Christ</hi> be dishonoured, <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> cannot be honoured: to acknowledg a <hi>Jehovah</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> do, one great supream power that made Heaven and earth as the <hi>Turks</hi> do, and not to acknowledg a <hi>Christ,</hi> is but to place an Idol in the room of God, and to embrace their own shadow and figment. The <hi>Father</hi> who is invisible, <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Calvin</hi> in 1 Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 23. Ioh. 8. 19. Ioh. 14. 9, 7. 2 Cor. 4. 6. Ioh. 15. 22.</note> hath only manifested himself to be served or saving in <hi>Christ:</hi> the bare majesty of God, must needs with its brightness and glory dazle our eyes, yea he is a <hi>consuming fire</hi> without the <hi>Son:</hi> All confess a <hi>God</hi> is to be worshipt, 'tis imbred in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but yet serving him out of <hi>Christ,</hi> their minds meerly vanish: and hence 'tis that there are so many false worships
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115037:10"/> and fictitious Deities in the world. As the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> are not separated in essence or operation, so neither must they be in our worship and honour: In the <hi>Son</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> is both honoured and despis'd: <hi>Whosoever denieth the Son, the same hath not the Father,</hi> 1 Joh. 2 23. he hath him not so as to worship him, he hath him not so as to receive any good from him: So <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>He that honoureth not the Son, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth not the Father:</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> is the <hi>only way</hi> unto the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> and therefore the Heathens, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 12. may well be <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> said there to be <hi>without God,</hi> they being likewise said to be <hi>without Christ.</hi> And this <hi>is</hi> not only in regard that the <hi>Son</hi> and the <hi>Father</hi> are of <hi>one essence and nature, (I and the Father are one,</hi> Joh 10. 30. <hi>I in the Father and the Father in me, Joh.</hi> 14. 11.) but because it hath <hi>pleased the Father</hi> to advance his <hi>Son</hi> unto that <hi>dignity</hi> which he will have all the world to acknowledg, under pain of eternall damnation: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 22. <hi>He hath committed all judgment to the Son,</hi> by way of execution and manifestation, and hath <hi>sealed him, Joh</hi> 6. 27. giving him the sanction of his authority, for the discharging of his Office: and <hi>hath made him Lord and Christ,</hi> Acts 2. 36. <hi>and hath given all things into his hand,</hi> Joh. 3. 35. <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 7; 8. Phil. 2. 9.</note> so that this is the true and the legitimate proving of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to the <hi>Father,</hi> when we embrace and receive the <hi>Son:</hi> The accepting of <hi>Christ</hi> is the great Commandement of God, and without this, all our services are disobediences. And hence we may gather, if the <hi>Father</hi> be our God, and be served only in the <hi>Son,</hi> that all the Patriarchs who had God for their Portion, as <hi>Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, David,</hi> and the holy men of old, did every one serve him in the <hi>Son,</hi> the promised <hi>Messiah;</hi> and 'tis this <hi>Messiah</hi> that we love and believe in, who was <hi>the way, the truth, and the life,</hi> to all those Saints of old. And hence 'tis likewise evident, if we sincerely submit our selves to the <hi>Son,</hi> accepting him to all those purposes for which the <hi>Father</hi> appointed him; as namely, to be served by us, as well as to be a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of us; to prepare us for Heaven, as well as to prepare Heaven for us: that the <hi>Father</hi> is ours, and that he will sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115037:10"/> and draw forth himself unto us, suitably to all the wants and exegencies of our souls, as our soul-satisfying portion. So much may suffice for the <hi>first</hi> branch in this second part, and that is the <hi>Object,</hi> the <hi>Son.</hi> But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Act</hi> in which we are to be imployed about the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Son,</hi> and that is to <hi>Kiss him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are (besides severall other sorts of <hi>Kisses</hi> mentioned in the Scripture, these two) eminently observable:</p>
            <p>The <hi>first</hi> is of <hi>Love;</hi> a <hi>Kiss</hi> bestowed upon an inferior by a superior, and by equals upon one another: and so you read <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of <hi>Jacobs</hi> kissing of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manasseh,</hi> Gen. 48. 10. <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 16. 1 Cor. 16. 10. Precibus finitis nos invicem osculo saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, amoris symbolo. <hi>Just. Mart.</hi> 2. <hi>Apol.</hi>
               </note> and so you finde a <hi>holy Kiss</hi> mentioned, and of it speaks <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> Ap. 2. though afterwards it being abused and becoming an occasion of wantonness in the Church, it was left off and prohibited.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is a <hi>Kise of homage and duty</hi> from the inferior to the superior, and this was a symboll or a token of <hi>subjection</hi> and honour: and thus <hi>Xenophon</hi> speaks of the <hi>Persians,</hi> that they were wont to give it to their Kings: and thus <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us concerning the souldiers, that they were every one of them ambitious to kiss <hi>Catoes</hi> hands; and so vassals were wont to do unto those to whom they gave <hi>homage</hi> by the kissing with the mouth, shewing, that they had faithfull hearts towards them, and mouthes ready to speak for them; thus I understand that <hi>Kiss</hi> that is spoken <note place="margin">Q. os. fidele domino suo▪ osserens.</note> of 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 1. where you read, that <hi>Samuel having anointed Saul, and poured oyl upon him, he kissed him</hi> as being his so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign to whom he would shew his loyalty and <hi>subjection:</hi> And this <hi>Kiss</hi> of <hi>subjection</hi> was not only used among persons in <hi>a civil,</hi> but also in a <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> way of adoration, and so the Heathens gave kisses unto their Idols; so you read <hi>Job</hi> 31. 26, 27. <hi>Job</hi> saith, <hi>If I beheld the Sun when it shined, or the Moon walking in brightness. And my heart hath been secretly enticed or my mouth hath kissed my hand.</hi> Because (as <hi>Molerus</hi> notes) they were not able to reach their supposed deity which they worshipped, so as to kiss <hi>it,</hi> they did stretch forth their hands <hi>toward</hi> that which they worshipped, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115037:11"/> then they kissed their hand in token of <hi>subjection</hi> to it. And thus I understand that place, 1 <hi>King</hi> 19. 18. where God saith, <hi>I have left seven thousand in Israel, all the knees which have not bowed unto Baal, and every mouth which hath not kissed him.</hi> And so, <hi>Hos.</hi> 13 2. there the Lord speaks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning those that worshipped the Calves, they called one upon another to <hi>Kiss the Calves.</hi> Thus <hi>Minutius Felix</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caecilius simu, lacro serapidis denotato ut vulgus super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitiosus solet, manum ori admovens, os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum labiis pressit. <hi>Minut Fel.</hi> in <hi>Oct.</hi> Affectatione Caelestia ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi, ad solis ortum labia vibratis <hi>&amp;c. Tert. Apol.</hi> 16.</note> speaks of one <hi>Caecilius,</hi> that looking upon an Image, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the custome of the superstitious vulgar, kist his his hand with his lips; And <hi>Tertullian</hi> speaks of this, saying, that the Heathens were wont at the rising of the Sun, every one to give kisses unto their hands in token of subjection to that their dumb deity; and by the way, it seems not to be without the providentiall wisdom of God, that the Sun which the Heathens did so frequently worship for their God, should have in the Hebrew a word that signifies a <hi>servant, shemesh,</hi> the Sun coming from <hi>shamash,</hi> to <hi>serve,</hi> as noting the unfitness of making that to be a Lord, which was appointed to be a servant to us, to hold the Candle, or to go before us with the Lanthorn, and to be the common servant of the world. (But that by the way.)</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Kiss</hi> here mentioned in the <hi>Text,</hi> I understand, that of this <hi>second</hi> sort, even such an one as denotes sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missive and humble <hi>subjection</hi> given by way of homage and loyalty unto the <hi>Lord Jesus.</hi> To <hi>Kiss the Son,</hi> is to be <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>By this</hi> Kiss <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ction is in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed;</hi>
               </note> to him, and to take him for our alone supream Lord and Governour. This is intended by this command of <hi>kissing,</hi> in the <hi>generall,</hi> but more particularly.</p>
            <p>There are sundry duties expressing this respect and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection comprehended in the same. As <note place="margin">And shewn,</note>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>An honorable opinion and high estimation of the Son</hi> Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that are high in place, should be high in their Subjects <note place="margin">In h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gh estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> thoughts: Despising them in the <hi>heart</hi> will make way for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching them with the <hi>tongue.</hi> The Subjects of <hi>David,</hi> (the type of Christ in this <hi>Psalm)</hi> thought him <hi>worth ten</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 3.</note>
               <hi>thousand of them.</hi> 'Twas <hi>Corah</hi>'s sinne to think, that <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were but as the rest of the people. Christ Jesus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115037:11"/> is to be lookt upon by the greatest, as the <hi>chiefest of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand,</hi> and to <hi>them</hi> he is to be <hi>precious.</hi> God would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to say, <hi>Who is the Lord,</hi> in a way of contempt? Kings should rather say, <hi>Who is as the Lord,</hi> by way of <hi>respect!</hi> 'Tis the common sinne of great ones, to have eyes so dazled with the Sunne-shine of worldly glory, as to see no excellency in Christ; as a man whose weak eyes have been overcome with the brightness of the Sunne, can see nothing, though laid never so plainly before him. Hence 'tis, they despise the spiritual beauty of his Ordinances, ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and servants, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> Christ is <hi>small</hi> to him, to whom the world is <hi>great. Herod and his men of warre mockt and set him at naught;</hi> And this is the ordinary usage that still Christ meets with in the world; The outside-meanness and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptibleness of the wayes of Christ, a proud Potentate will hardly brook, no Christ will please them without external Grandeur: Beauties in fancy, outside-glisterings, and well-acted vanities, so affect them, that solid glory is neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them. They, to whom Christ is a <hi>stumbling stone</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his smalness, and appearing despicableness, shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after finde him a <hi>stone to crush them,</hi> when he fals upon them, and dasheth them in peeces. Worldly great ones often honour wickedness in robes, and contemn holiness in rags. Him, who hath his Throne in Heaven, they labour to make their foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stool upon Earth. And this is the reason that God oft makes them who are adored as gods by men, to become the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> lowest of men, and poureth <hi>shamefull spewing upon their glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In high almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> Est vis quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam per quam princeps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliat sibi in hominum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, singula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem quandam admirationem, &amp; veneratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem <hi>Gerh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng. Pol.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, This Subjection and Homage to the Sonne, imports the high <hi>Admiration</hi> due to him. It is a part of his honourable Title, he is called <hi>Wonderfull,</hi> Isa. 9 6. and <hi>Gerhard</hi> speaking concerning Magistrates saith, They are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Scripture <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Glories</hi> and <hi>Dignities,</hi> because they cause in Subjects a singular <hi>admiration</hi> and <hi>veneration.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in dignity respected, are more or less admired, and <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> is not the least part of the respect given to them. And therefore where we reade in Scripture of <hi>respecting of persons,</hi> as that God is not a <hi>respecter of persons,</hi> 2 Chron. 19 7.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115037:12"/> Deut. 10. 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Septuagint</hi> they render them, God is no <hi>wonderer,</hi> no admirer at persons: And <hi>Jude</hi> is thought to follow them, where he taxeth some for unduly respecting of others, <hi>By having mens persons in admiration;</hi> And the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> 2 King 5. 1. where it is said, that <hi>Naaman was honourable,</hi> they translate it, <hi>He was wondered at, in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi> And thus our Lord Jesus is then <hi>honoured</hi> as our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Lord, when we look upon him as <hi>wonderfull,</hi> and admire him. The glorious Angels who <hi>adore</hi> him, also <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire</hi> him; and particularly in regard of mans redemption by the mysterious concurrence of the Divine and Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 16. Ephes. 3. 10, 11 1 Pet. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in one Person, a mysterious depth, which they are not able to fathom, though they do <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> stoop to pry into it, with never so much curiosity, and are never such industrious Students in this Divinity. A work which any creature was so farre from contriving, that it had been bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy <note place="margin">Niexemb. de Ador.</note> without divine Revelation once to have imagin'd it. Oh admired mystery, for God to begin to be what he was not, and yet to remain what he was; for the Natures to be united, and yet unmixed; to be unmixed, and yet inseparably united; for a reconciliation to be found out between God and man, by the Marriage of the Natures of both; for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the world, to be made of a woman; for the Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting Father, to become a Childe; for him that measur'd <hi>the Heavens with a span,</hi> to become a Childe of a <hi>span long;</hi> for him whom the Heavens cannot contain, to lodge in the womb; yea for the <hi>King of glory</hi> to become a worm, that worms might be advanced even to Angelical Dignity. How admirable is our Lord in his Life, Death, Resurrection, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of his Church, Conquest over his Enemies! Who ever heard of a God to be poor! Majesty to lie buried in the chips; A Physician to cure, with giving his own Bloud for the Potion; Of Rebels, to be pardon'd by their <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Cyril. Hier. Catech, 14.</note> killing the Ambassadour (the Kings only Sonne;) Of one that was <hi>dead,</hi> not only to arise by his own power, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>free among the dead, to be the Person that should free the living;</hi> Of Powers and Principalities, to be vanquished
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115037:12"/> in frail flesh; Of Life, to be caused by death; Of Subjects, to be increased by being cut off, and a Kingdom to be enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by losing; Of one who was once a despicable, poor worm, in whom all sufferings and disgraces centred, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Judge of the whole world, (attended with millions of such servants, every one whereof shall shine more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than the Sunne in his beauty, to whose lustre, the glory of all the Kings of the Earth, is no more than a black coal to the Sun beams) and before the Tribunal of this Judg the greatest Emperours of the Earth to be the arraigned and trembling malefactours, accounting the loads of Rocks and Mountains; light and easie, in comparison of his displeasure. In one word, Infinitely admirable is this glorious Person, in his <hi>Conditions</hi> of Humiliation and Exaltation; Admirable in his <hi>endowments</hi> of Power, Wisdom, Love, Holiness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Admirable in his <hi>dispensations</hi> towards all his Subjects, high, low, good, bad, in Heaven, in Earth, Hell. And surely, if such a Lord as this, be not served with <hi>admiration,</hi> he is not served like himself, like Gods Son, or our Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This Subjection to the Sonne of God our su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Lord, betokens <hi>Humiliation, and the abasing of our</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Self humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
               <hi>selves before him.</hi> You read when the people of <hi>Israel</hi> stood by the Gyants, they looked upon themselves as <hi>Gras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers.</hi> Oh when we think of this highly advanced Sonne of God, who is higher than Heavens and Angels, how should all knees <hi>bow before him,</hi> and the greatest be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed! <hi>David</hi> saith, when he beheld the Moon and the Stars, <hi>What is man that thou remembrest him, or the sonne of man</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 8.</note>
               <hi>that thou visitest him?</hi> And what self-debasing thoughts should then possess us, when we consider the great God that made these things, before whom these, and all the world are <hi>less than nothing?</hi> Great <hi>Abraham</hi> cals himself <hi>Dust and ashes,</hi> when he came before him: Yea the Angels <hi>worship</hi> him. <hi>Michael (who is like to the Lord)</hi> is the name of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, bestow'd upon the Archangel. The highest on earth must remember there is an higher in Heaven, and take heed how they resent, if not how they receive Titles of honour.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115037:13"/> The greatest care of most great ones is, how to <hi>get</hi> honour; truly our greatest care should be how to <hi>use</hi> honour, how not to be proud of it when we have it, <hi>It is a hard thing to be low with contentedness, and to be high with humility.</hi> It's a rare and noble temper, when that excellency which all others observe, is only hid to him who hath it; and as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> who (speaking with God) pull'd off his <hi>shoes,</hi> and <hi>hid</hi> his <hi>face,</hi> to discover by acknowledgement, our infirmities, and conceal the comeliness of any thing wherein we seem to excel. Humility is the sutablest Robe for a King, who thinks (as he ought) of this <hi>King of Kings.</hi> Humility is the ornament of Angels, and the deformity of Devils. The command of being <hi>cloathed with humility</hi> belongs to Princes as much as (if not more than) to beggars. In conditions of highness, <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 5.</note> there's greatest heed to be taken of high-mindedness. Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and worldly lowness are the food of Humility. Riches and Honours are the fewel of pride. <hi>David, Asa</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (though good, yet) shew'd themselves <hi>men</hi> in being unduly lifted up by worldly glory, and they all smarted for it suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently. I have heard of a Bird that is so little, and so light and feathery, that it alwayes flies with a stone in its mouth, lest otherwise the windes should carry it away. In high conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we shall easily lose our selves, unless we carefully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve Humility in the heart.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This subjection to the Sonne of God, as our Supream Lord, imports, <hi>Confidence in him, dependance upon</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>him, and trusting to him for all good.</hi> This is a duty princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally <note place="margin">Trust and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> incumbent on Potentates, <hi>Some trust in Chariots, and some in horses, but they must remember the Name of this great Lord.</hi> It's hard to have the world <hi>much,</hi> and to trust it <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi> God sets the greatest in <hi>slippery places,</hi> that they may trust to Christ for sustentation. 'Tis here said to Kings and Rulers, <hi>Blessed are all those that trust in him.</hi> It may be the sin oft of <hi>us</hi> in subjection, to trust in <hi>you,</hi> but it cannot be <hi>your</hi> sin to trust in <hi>him.</hi> There are two things that men are most ready sinfully to trust in, the one is their <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saicall righteousness,</hi> and the other is their <hi>worldly great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness:</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115037:13"/> Now he that would take the Son for his supream Lord, must trust to neither of these reeds; not to his <hi>righteousness,</hi> he must throw that away, though it seem his gold. If a man be in the water ready to be drowned, and hath in one hand a handfull of pibbles, and in the other an handfull of gold, there being a cable thrown out to save him, he must cast away his gold out of the one hand, as well as his pibbles out of the other. <hi>Luther</hi> makes the application, when he adviseth to take more heed of our seeming good works, lest they hinder us from Christ, then of our sinnes. If God hath appointed that we should go out of our selves for a <hi>vital</hi> subsistence to things below, to Bread for food, to Cloathes for warmth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> much more will he have us to go out of our selves for a <hi>blessed</hi> subsistence not to his <hi>worldly greatness:</hi> when the world is but <hi>promising,</hi> Christ is seldom trusted. It's observed by some, that the Book of <hi>Ecclesiastes</hi> is prefixed before that of <hi>Canticles,</hi> because <hi>Ecclesiastes,</hi> takes us off from the Creature, by shewing its emptiness, and <hi>Canticles</hi> woos un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Christ, by shewing his worth and fulness. We can hardly be brought to look upon Christ as one that is fully and solely to be trusted to, till God gives to see the weakness and vanity of all creature dependencies; so long as a man stands upon his legs in the water, he ventures not himself upon the stream to bear him up: Till we see our selves <hi>fatherless,</hi> we shall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go to <hi>Christ</hi> to find mercy. The <hi>Vine,</hi> the <hi>Ivy,</hi> the <hi>Hop,</hi> the <hi>Wood bind,</hi> are taught by nature to cling and wind about stronger Trees; and hence 'tis, that God takes even great ones often off from their own legs, and shews them the brittleness and vanity of their creature crutches, before (or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily) he doth any great good either to them or by them and seasons them commonly (like timber) by wants and sufferings, before he either builds them up, or builds up o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> This <hi>subjection</hi> to the Son of God as our supream <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Lord, imports the <hi>fearing and reverencing of him.</hi> I meane <note place="margin">Fear.</note> an ingenuous <hi>fear,</hi> the <hi>fear</hi> of a loyal <hi>subject</hi> toward a gracious Prince; not that of slaves, under and for wrath, this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115037:14"/> is <hi>bondage,</hi> that is <hi>duty,</hi> to fear him as voluntary <hi>subjects,</hi> not as unvoluntary <hi>slaves:</hi> to fear him, not because he sets himself against <hi>sinners,</hi> but because sin sets it self against <hi>him.</hi> First fear <hi>him,</hi> and then fear his <hi>wrath,</hi> Fear him more out of sense of <hi>duty enjoyned,</hi> then of <hi>danger threatned.</hi> Let your fear <hi>therefore</hi> be regardfull of Gods <hi>wrath,</hi> because it proceeds from a faith which reposeth it self on his <hi>mercy.</hi> Its no cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardize for the most warlike Emperour, to fear offending this <hi>greatest Lord:</hi> true valour stands in stooping to him, and fearing of sin: 'tis not magnanimity but madness to fight against the <hi>Lord of Hosts:</hi> it is not courage but fool-hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to go boldly to <hi>hell,</hi> and only proceeds from the ignorance of <hi>danger;</hi> like that of the silly <hi>Americans,</hi> who press upon the mouth of the Musquet, because they are unacquainted with its force: Men of greatest courage, have been most fearfull <hi>of,</hi> and sorrowfull <hi>for</hi> sin. <hi>Josiah</hi> was <hi>stout hearted,</hi> and yet <hi>tender-hearted. David</hi> who had <hi>kild the Lyon and the Bear, yet waters his bed with tears;</hi> and he who had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown <hi>Armies,</hi> and set his feet upon the neck of <hi>Goliah,</hi> is himself laid flat by one poor <hi>Prophet.</hi> There is mercy enough in this <hi>great Lord,</hi> to allure the most <hi>trembling sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> and majesty enough in this <hi>gracious Prince,</hi> to dismay the <hi>stoutest rebel.</hi> Particularly fear him in <hi>that</hi> wherein you are commonly most fearless, I mean your worldly rejoycing. In your greatest abundance you must not <hi>feast your selves</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 12.</note>
               <hi>without fear.</hi> You must know, that though you be Lords of rich well-furnished tables, <hi>Christ</hi> is more the Lord of your <hi>enjoyments</hi> then your selves: 'Tis the supream Lord who will call you to an account, how you have used his creatures, and whether you have not <hi>kickt</hi> against him when you have been <hi>fall:</hi> and thus <hi>Musculus</hi> interprets the foregoing verse, <note place="margin">Admonentur, ne, dum aliis imperantes exultan▪ timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Dei obli viscantur. <hi>Musc.</hi> in <hi>Loc.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Rejoyce before him with trembling,</hi> that is, when you are in the midst of your worldly <hi>enjoyments,</hi> and when you rejoyce in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>men</hi> (as the Disciples did once in having <hi>devils) subject unto you.</hi> Even then take heed lest you forget your <hi>supream Lord,</hi> who hath not lost his propriety in any thing you have, by his giving it to you.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115037:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> This <hi>subjection</hi> to <hi>him</hi> as our <hi>supream Lord,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> appeares in the way of <hi>acknowledging him,</hi> celebration and <note place="margin">Praise.</note> praising of his Name, for all the good that he hath done for his subjects. This tribute of <hi>praises</hi> is given him at large, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was slain, to receive power, and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honour, and glory, and blessing.</hi> If you have a <hi>power</hi> to do or receive any good, this <hi>supream Lord</hi> must be magnified for it. <hi>I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 13.</note>
               <hi>can do all things through Christ that strengthens me.</hi> If God hath pardoned sins, the <hi>Bloud of the Lamb</hi> must be magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for it; If deliverance from <hi>wrath</hi> he bestowed, <hi>Jesus</hi> must have the praise; If worldly maintenance, our very life, motion, and being, must be <hi>acknowledged</hi> to be from <hi>him. By him all things consist, and he upholds all things by the word of his power,</hi> Heb. 1. 3. Col. 1. 15. And <hi>of him, and from him, and for him, are all things.</hi> If victories be given, it is by this <hi>Lord of Host,</hi> he it is that orders the great transactions of the world, and <hi>changes the times and seasons,</hi> and puls down one, and sets up another. If at any time any good work be done <hi>for</hi> us, <hi>in</hi> us, <hi>by</hi> us, <hi>Christ</hi> must have the <hi>praise</hi> thereof. I read of <hi>Constantine,</hi> that when he had built many Hospitals for the poor, he wrote <hi>Jesus</hi> up on every entrance into them; He would not take any glory to himself, but gave all to <hi>Christ. Now unto the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 17.</note>
               <hi>eternall, immortall, invisible, the onely wise God, be honour and glory, for ever and ever.</hi> 'Tis reported that a certain King being in a Ship upon the Sea, and his Crown falling from him into the water, a subject of his in the Ship, would needs offer to dive into the Sea to fetch back the Crown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he adventures to dive, and brings up the Crown with him, but being not able to bring it back in his hands, he puts it on his head, and the King (they say,) rewarded him for bringing back the Crown with him, but punish't him with the loss of his head, for putting the Crown on it. God will not endure to have that honour given to the creature, that is only due to <hi>Christ;</hi> Fetch up his honour if you see it fall, but you must take heed lest you set it upon your own
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115037:15"/> heads. When <hi>Herod</hi> unduly accepted of applaus, the Angel of <note place="margin">Act. 12. 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Lord smote him, and made him <hi>worms meat</hi> presently; Just is God to hinder the creature from incroaching on his own prerogative: Their's none fit to waite upon the <hi>King of Glory,</hi> but such as give all <hi>glory</hi> to this <hi>King. By the grace of God I am, what I am,</hi> (saith holy and humble <hi>Paul)</hi> in respect of good, yea, 'tis by his grace (as <hi>Austin</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently) That thou <hi>art not, what thou art not,</hi> in respect of <hi>sin,</hi> and <hi>hast not, what thou hast not,</hi> in respect of <hi>punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> It's a naturall evil to make our selves the centers of our own excellencies: and God singles out those to be the most notable monuments of his justice, and their own folly, who share with him in <hi>divine</hi> prerogatives. Nothing is more ordinary then for high services to usher in that <hi>pride,</hi> which often hurts the performers; There's no poyson that hurts so delightfully and dangerously, as reflection on our seeming deservings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> This <hi>subjection</hi> to the <hi>supream Lord</hi> appeares in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> the way of <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>him</hi> in all transactions, in taking heed <note place="margin">Obedience.</note> that nothing be done against the commands of this great <hi>Lord.</hi> The King (as you read, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 12.) had the Crown put upon <hi>his head,</hi> and the <hi>testimony into his hand.</hi> And God commands, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 18. That he should <hi>write him a copy of the Law.</hi> As God hath put his livery upon the <hi>backs,</hi> so must his work be put into the <hi>hands</hi> of Rulers; Though Kings are often titular Kings over people, yet they must not be titular servants unto <hi>Christ;</hi> It is not enough for them to <hi>call him Lord,</hi> they must also <hi>do his will.</hi> His commands must be obeyed 1. <hi>Absolutely.</hi> Thus, <hi>Him onely shalt thou serve,</hi> Mat. 6. 24. Men must be obeyed, as they obey <hi>Christ.</hi> When <hi>Christ</hi> commands, consider <hi>who</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, not <hi>what</hi> is or <hi>why</hi> 'tis commanded: When men command, enquire <hi>what</hi> is commanded, not <hi>who</hi> commands; (that for which God will call thee to an account, in reference to obeying of man, is not <hi>what man</hi> hast thou obeyed, but <hi>wherein</hi> hast thou obeyed him? and (as <hi>Augustine</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently) <hi>what matters it under whose command or government</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quid refert sub cujus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio vivat ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo moritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, si illi qui im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perant, ad ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua &amp; impia nen cogeant. <hi>Aug.</hi> de civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>ad init.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115037:15"/>
               <hi>dying man lives, so long as he who governs, commands not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull things?)</hi> The commands of earthly Rulers, are rules <hi>ruled</hi> by another an higher rule. The commands of <hi>Christ,</hi> are rules purely ruling: he alone cannot err, his will is the rule of all righteousness. 2. This supreme Lord must be obeyed <hi>universally</hi> in all his commands, none must pick and chuse his precepts, nor <hi>prefer one before another. Jehu</hi> seemed a uery obedient servant, till he came to a <hi>command</hi> that made against his <hi>interest:</hi> he <hi>walked,</hi> yea he <hi>ran,</hi> all the while his path was <hi>smooth,</hi> but when it began to be (as he conceived) <hi>stony</hi> and <hi>rugged,</hi> he soon <hi>halted:</hi> but we must obey the <hi>Son</hi> in the most difficult commands, and walk in a <hi>rugged way,</hi> as well as in a <hi>smooth grass-plat,</hi> obeying Christ in things that cross <hi>carnal interest,</hi> yea <hi>carnal reason.</hi> 3. <hi>Christ</hi> must be obeyed <hi>willingly</hi> and <hi>ingenuously,</hi> with a love to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> and <hi>commander,</hi> not only because of his power to <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish.</hi> Obedience to this power must be for <hi>conscience sake.</hi> If the eye be not to the <hi>command,</hi> the servant acts not with <hi>obedience,</hi> though the <hi>thing</hi> be done which is commanded. Its very possible, that a work for the <hi>matter</hi> agreeable to the <hi>command,</hi> may yet be an act of disobedience in respect of <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 9. Col. 3. 23. Psal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. Joh. 4. Si non possunt a domino libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri fieri, suam servitutem ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si quodam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do liberam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt <hi>Aug.</hi> de civ. Dei. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> the intent of the performer: This Lord must be served <hi>from the heart,</hi> and he must be <hi>served in the spirit.</hi> This Lord as he was his fathers servant, <hi>delighted to do his will,</hi> 'twas his <hi>meat and drink.</hi> This willingness makes the service <hi>easie</hi> to the <hi>servant,</hi> and <hi>acceptable</hi> to the <hi>master. Lastly,</hi> Christ must be served <hi>perpetually,</hi> there must be no end of <hi>working,</hi> till of <hi>living:</hi> the <hi>dead</hi> are they who <hi>rest from their labours.</hi> Life and labour must be of equall continuance: none can <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi> too soon or <hi>continue</hi> too long in Christs service: Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullness <hi>to the death,</hi> hath the only promise of the <hi>Crown of life.</hi> If the service of Christ be <hi>bad,</hi> why do any enter into it? if <hi>good</hi> (as 'tis infinitely the best) why do they not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly and lastly,</hi> Subjection to this supream Lord, is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> seen <hi>in zeal for the promotion of his honour,</hi> and that both in <note place="margin">Zeal.</note> the <hi>furthering</hi> and setting up of whatever tends to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115037:16"/> and in <hi>removing</hi> and opposing whatever disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours him. Rulers must respect all <hi>Christs</hi> good subjects, as their <hi>follow-servants,</hi> and particularly his <hi>Ambassadours</hi> must be regarded, not discountenanced, much less destroyed with <hi>force</hi> or <hi>famine:</hi> their <hi>double</hi> labour must not be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with scarce a <hi>single</hi> maintenance: They must not be left to the courtesie of those, who though they account <hi>enough</hi> for themselves but <hi>a little,</hi> yet they think <hi>a little</hi> for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister <hi>too much.</hi> Its not enough for faithfull Ministers to be kept from being <hi>batterd</hi> and stormd by cruel persecutors, unless also from being <hi>starved</hi> by common Protestants. In short, the <hi>great King</hi> cannot have your subjection, if his <hi>messengers</hi> have your scorn: If it comes to that once, there will be <hi>no remedy</hi> for you, his wrath will burn, their disgraces he accounts his own, he will not put them up. His <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>worship</hi> must be establisht, the sanctifying of his <hi>day</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 14. 3. 2 Chro. 34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. Nehem. 13. 19</note> enjoyned. <hi>Asa commanded Juda to seek the Lord. Josiah made the people to serve the Lord. Nehemiah commanded that the gates should be shut, and charged that they should not be opened, till after the Sabbath.</hi> Zeal for the honour of this supream Lord, must also be shewn in <hi>opposing</hi> his enemies. Do those <hi>kiss the Son,</hi> who make much of those that would dethrone, yea <hi>kill</hi> the Son? You heard in the morning excellently, <note place="margin">M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Caryl</hi> preaching.</note>
               <hi>If we be cold in regarding the glory of God, his anger will be hot against us.</hi> That passage was my <hi>Text</hi> in other words, <hi>Kiss the Son lest he be angry.</hi> You then likewise heard, <hi>God will not dwell in a polluted house;</hi> nor will he drink of a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <note place="margin">Nescit de tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bato fonte amicus bibere. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> fountain where seducers and sectaries dabble with their errours and ungodly opinions, and where they mud and spoil those sweet streams of the word and all divine institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Ample testimony is given to <hi>David, Asa, Jehoshaphat, Hezekiah, Josiah,</hi> of their zeal for religion: nor ever is the <note place="margin">2 Chro. 31. 1. 1 Chro. 17. 6. 2 King. 23. 6, 7, 8.</note> contrary mentioned in any of the other Kings, but as their great sin and infamy. Nor will the names of <hi>Constantine, Theodosius, Justinian,</hi> cease to be precious for their care of the Church. If zeal for God in suppressing of offenders <note place="margin">2 King. 18. 4. 2 Chro. 14. 4.</note> against the first Table, were the Magistrates <hi>chief</hi> duty and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115037:16"/> commendation in the <hi>old Testament,</hi> must not lukewarmness <note place="margin">1 King. 15. 12, 13. 2 Chro. 34. 33.</note> in suffering them, be his great <hi>sin</hi> and dishonour in the <hi>new.</hi> Clear precept there is <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. for punishing them: and (as <hi>Piscator</hi> proves) we have no warrant from God to abolish the <hi>Judicial,</hi> as it commands the punishing of sins against the <hi>Moral</hi> Law. Are not the <hi>punishments</hi> as immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table as the <hi>offence?</hi> Is the offence a standing offence, and shall the punishment be a <hi>temporary</hi> and vanishing punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Is the inclination of people to such wickedness less than heretofore? Is not the ground of the command, <hi>viz. that Israel may hear and fear, and do no more such wickedness,</hi> a standing and <hi>perpetuall</hi> ground? Is the suffering the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est evils to be done, an execution of <hi>wrath</hi> upon <hi>evil doers?</hi> or <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> is the <hi>execution of wrath upon evil doers,</hi> consistent with the suffering the worst of them? Are we not to pray, that we may live <hi>a peaceable life</hi> under Magistrates, as well in all <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 2.</note> as <hi>honesty?</hi> Are either Rulers or people, less behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Lord Jesus</hi> in the <hi>new</hi> Testament, than they were in the <hi>old?</hi> Have we less <hi>light</hi> and <hi>love from</hi> Christ, or ought we to have less love <hi>to</hi> Christ than they had of old? or are peoples souls less precious now than they were then? Was it such a punishable wickedness heretofore to <hi>set up a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quomodo ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viunt Domino, nisi ea quae sunt contra Domini jus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum, religiosa severitate ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctunt. <hi>Musc. in</hi> Psal. 2. <hi>v. penult.</hi> Quis mente sobrius regibus dicat, nolite curare in reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no vestro, a quo defenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vel oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etur Ecclesia Domini vestri? <hi>Aug Ep.</hi> 8.</note>
               <hi>graven Image,</hi> and is it now become an offence more <hi>veniall</hi> and tolerable, to <hi>pull down</hi> (as much as lies in the power of an hereticall seducer) the <hi>express Image of the Father,</hi> by an open denying the <hi>Deity</hi> of the <hi>Son of God?</hi> Because no <hi>conscience</hi> can be touched, must all <hi>practices</hi> be suffered? <hi>Musculus</hi> excellently observes upon the <hi>verse</hi> going before my <hi>Text,</hi> that the <hi>civil Magistrate</hi> cannot be said to <hi>serve God,</hi> if he doth not exercise religious severity upon the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers of Gods Commands. Its not enough for him only as he is <hi>a man,</hi> to serve him, by <hi>trusting</hi> in him, <hi>praying</hi> to him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but he must <hi>serve</hi> him also as <hi>a Magistrate:</hi> (Who dares say, that the chief Magistrate of a Nation is only to <hi>honour</hi> God, and <hi>kiss the Son,</hi> as doth a Merchant or a Draper?) and how doth he serve him as a <hi>Magistrate,</hi> if he do nothing against the open enemies of this great <hi>King</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115037:17"/> and supream Lord, but carelesly suffer them to dishonour him, not regarding whether Religion stand or fall, be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed or maintained in his Kingdom? And to those who object, that we have no <hi>example</hi> in the <hi>Apostles</hi> writings, that any thing was desired of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> for the helping of the Church against these her enemies? the answer is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious: <note place="margin">Non inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur exemplum in Apostolicis literis, aliquid petitum a regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus terrae pro Ecclesiá &amp; contra ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micos Eccle fiae. Sed non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum impleba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur illa Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetia, &amp; nunc Reges intelli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gite, service Domino in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Adhuc enim illud implebatur quod in eodem Psalmo paulo superius dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Quare tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muerunt gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <hi>&amp;c</hi> adsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terunt Reges terrae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Tempo ibus Apostolorum &amp; Martyrum illud impleba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quod figuratum est quando Nebuchadnezar, pios &amp; justos cogebat adorare simula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra, &amp; recusantes in flaminas mittebat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unc autem &amp; illud impletur quod paulo post in eodem Rege figuratum est, cum conversus ad honorandum Deum verum, decrevit in egno suo, ut quicun{que} blasphemaret Deum Sidrac, Misac &amp; Abednego, poenis debitis ubjaceret. <hi>Aug. Ep.</hi> 48. <hi>pag mibe</hi> 170.</note> The Apostles lived under Infidels and Persecutors, who were so far from <hi>defending</hi> Christianity, that they <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrd</hi> the Christians: And thus <hi>Augustin</hi> answers in his Eight and fourtieth <hi>Epistle</hi> written to one <hi>Vincentius,</hi> where he hath these words: <hi>'Tis true, saith he, we finde no such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, but then was not fullfild the Prophecy in the second Psalm;</hi> Be wise now therefore O ye Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Serve the Lord with fear: <hi>but then was fulfiled that which before in the second Psalm was mentioned:</hi> Why did the Gentiles rage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Kings of the earth set themselves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> against the Lord and against his anointed, <hi>&amp;c. In the Times of the Apostles and Martyrs, was fulfilled what was figured in the command of</hi> Nebuchadnezzar, <hi>that all the righteous should worship his Image, and that they who refused this command should be thrown into the fire. But now in our times, is fulfilled that which a little after was figured in the same King, who being himself brought to honour the true God, made a Decree, that whosoever blasphemed the God of</hi> Shadrach, Mesach <hi>and</hi> Abednego, <hi>should be punished severely: The first time of that King, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the primitive times, wherein the Christians living under Kings that were Infidels, suffered instead of the wicked: and the latter time of that King, signified these after-ages, wherein Kings being converted, the wicked suffer instead of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This for the opening of the <hi>second</hi> Particular in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>duty</hi> of kissing the Son. The <hi>third</hi> follows,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115037:17"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Argument</hi> by which Rulers are put upon this duty <note place="margin">Third branch of the Doctrine.</note> of <hi>kissing the Son, lest he be angry.</hi> There are two things in this branch considerable by way of explication,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>First,</hi> The <hi>certainty</hi> of the Sons anger if Rulers will not <hi>Kiss</hi> him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Severity</hi> and <hi>dreadfulness</hi> of this anger here threatned, to put them upon <hi>kissing</hi> the Son.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>first</hi> of these, the <hi>certainty</hi> of the Sons anger, is clearly intended in the word, <hi>lest, lest he be angry.</hi> For <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> though the word be sometime used in Scripture as a note of doubt and hesitation, yet it here imports <hi>certainty:</hi> as <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Ye shall not eat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>lest ye die.</hi> For there was no doubt but <hi>Adam</hi> by eating of the forbidden fruit, should become <hi>subject</hi> unto <hi>death,</hi> as neither in this place, can it be doubted, but that they shall be destroyed by the <hi>anger</hi> of the Son, who will refuse to <hi>Kiss</hi> him. And the <hi>certainty</hi> thereof is manifest upon these grounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> The <hi>certainty</hi> of their ruine by the Sons anger is clear, by considering the <hi>truth</hi> of his <hi>threatning</hi> against them. <hi>Truth is that which makes every threatning smart, and every promise sweet.</hi> Take away <hi>truth</hi> from a <hi>threatning,</hi> and the greater the woe is which is <hi>threatned:</hi> the more ridiculous is the <hi>threatning,</hi> it being but as a charge of Powder in a Gun without a Bullet. If the Word be <hi>true,</hi> the woes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusers of <hi>subjection</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> must needs be <hi>certain. Deut.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Whosoever will not hearken unto my words which he shall speak in my Name, I will require it of him.</hi> And this is repeated again, <hi>Act</hi> 3. 23. <hi>Every soul that will not hear that Prophet, shall be destroyed from among the people.</hi> And that Scripture, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 27. is as full of <hi>certainty</hi> as of <hi>severity. Those mine enemies, that would not I should rule over them, bring them hither and slay them before my face</hi> Let them be of what kind, rank, degree soever, yet if <hi>enemies,</hi> they must be slaine. And 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Vengeance in flaming fire</hi> is denounced against those that <hi>obey not the Gospel of Christ,</hi> and what is that but to <hi>Kiss the Son,</hi> which is the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Gospel, and the Law of Faith. All these
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115037:18"/>
               <hi>threatnings</hi> without <hi>truth,</hi> are but scare-crows. He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <hi>them</hi> is <hi>true,</hi> yea <hi>truth</hi> it self; and as truely, as it's impossible <hi>for him to lie,</hi> shall they be executed on all those that will not <hi>Kiss</hi> him; God will not deny himself to gratify sinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>certainty</hi> of this destroying anger, appears <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by the <hi>great disproportion</hi> that is between this <hi>Son of God,</hi> and all the Sons of <hi>men.</hi> Oh infinite, amazing disproportion! <hi>Can your hands be strong, or can your hearts endure in the day wherein he will deale with you?</hi> Ezek. 22 14. There is a greater disproportion between the Son of God, and all his enemies, then there is between an Army of <hi>Angels</hi> and the least <hi>Ant</hi> that creeps upon a mole-hill; All the world before <hi>him</hi> is <hi>less then nothing;</hi> There is no way to fly from him, but by flying to him; All your abilities, and armies, and whatever is an <hi>arme of flesh,</hi> will vanish and wither in the <hi>day</hi> of his <hi>wrath.</hi> 'Twill be the vain desire of his stoutest enemies, that the <hi>Rocks and Mountains would fall upon them,</hi> to shelter them from his fury.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>certainty</hi> of the Sons anger appeares, in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that full <hi>authority</hi> which the Father hath given <hi>him,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire this <hi>Kiss of homage.</hi> He hath <hi>sealed</hi> him a commission for this purpose, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 27. Christ his <hi>authority</hi> hath the stamp of Divine sanction. <hi>The Father hath committed all judgment unto the Son, that all men should honour the Son, as they honour the Father,</hi> Joh. 5. 22. And he hath <hi>authority</hi> given him, to <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cute Judgment,</hi> Joh. 5. 27. And <hi>the Father hath committed all things into his hand,</hi> Joh. 3. 35. <hi>Ordained him to be Judge of quick and dead,</hi> Act. 10. 42. <hi>Made him Lord and Christ,</hi> Act 2. 36. Now, shall God authorize and commissionate his Son to be the great <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> of the world, and do you think that God will indure the abuse of his own glorious <hi>Institution,</hi> his eternal and merciful <hi>plot</hi> of <hi>infinite wisdom?</hi> And as the Father will exempt none from <hi>subjection</hi> to the Son, because he hath <hi>appointed</hi> and <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained</hi> him to be <hi>Lord of all,</hi> so neither will the Son suffer any to deny <hi>subjection</hi> to <hi>himself,</hi> because thereby his Father is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115037:18"/> who gave him <hi>authority</hi> to receive it. And hence Christ aggravates the sin of the Jews, in <hi>refusing</hi> him, by their dishonouring the Father: <hi>I am come</hi> (saith he) <hi>in my Fathers Name, and ye receive me not.</hi> And <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>Every tongue must confess that Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>certainty</hi> of this wrath against all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse <hi>subjection</hi> to the Son, is evident, because by that refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>he</hi> that is the <hi>onely deliverer from wrath</hi> is contemned: A great <hi>Saviour,</hi> yea, <hi>great salvation is neglected.</hi> The meanes of recovery <hi>despised,</hi> must needs make misery as <hi>inevitable,</hi> as 'tis <hi>inexcuseable.</hi> He who hath been in rebellion <hi>may die,</hi> but he who scornes a pardon <hi>must die.</hi> If a <hi>Saviour</hi> help not, who shall <hi>save?</hi> If the <hi>Father</hi> be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, the <hi>Son</hi> may interpose: But if the <hi>Son</hi> be angry, there is no <hi>Mediatour</hi> between God and a <hi>Mediatour.</hi> (Let the Papist say what he will) If mercy be our enemy, what then will Justice be? If the Gospel condemns, what doth the Law? He that is sick <hi>may die,</hi> but certainly he that will not submit to the onely meanes of cure <hi>must die.</hi> And a despiser of Christ, concludes himself under a necessity, (yea) of heightned condemnation; For, salvation offered, and yet neglected, needs must prove condemnation increased. How great is that destruction, where a <hi>Saviour</hi> is the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyer.</hi> No liquor more scalding then the oyl of mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The <hi>certainty</hi> of wrath appeares from the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness</hi> of God. <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the earth be</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>righteous?</hi> Either he must be righteous, or no Judge. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would he be righteous, nor God, should he love sin, and those who sinning, though they themselves be unable to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, will not accept of another to satisfie for them. Is it imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that God should lose his own <hi>nature</hi> to gratifie <hi>impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> If it be a <hi>righteous thing with God to render tribulation</hi> to them, would it not be unrighteous to bestow love upon <note place="margin">2 Thes. 1. 6.</note> them? Is God righteous in forgiving the sins of believers in Christ? and can he be likewise righteous in accepting the <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1. 9.</note> refusers of Christ?</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115037:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In this last branch we are to consider the <hi>severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of his anger, as well as its <hi>certainty.</hi> I might tell you <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pidltas ulciscendi. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> how anger is here attributed to the <hi>Son:</hi> not as it is described a desire of revenge, as betokening passion or perturbation of the mind, but as it doth comprehend two things.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>A will and a resolution to punish,</hi> and so you have it Rom. 1. 18. <hi>The wrath of God is revealed against all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness:</hi> i. e. the will of God to punish wicked men is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed and made known in their punishment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It doth comprehend <hi>the effects</hi> of that <hi>wrath,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> those plagues and judgments that the <hi>Son of God</hi> will lay upon those that refuse to <hi>kiss him:</hi> and thus Gods wrath is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently taken in Scripture: where you read, that <hi>the wrath of God comes upon the children of disobedience,</hi> Ephes. 5. 6. that is, the <hi>expressions</hi> of his <hi>wrath.</hi> So <hi>Matth</hi> 3. 7. <hi>Who</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 5. Rom. 2. 5.</note>
               <hi>hath warned you to slee from the wrath to come.</hi> Luk. 21. 23. <hi>Great wrath shall be upon this people.</hi> And here by the wrath of <hi>Christ,</hi> I understand the great discovery thereof in it's <hi>effects</hi> against wicked men.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>severity</hi> and dreadfulness of this <hi>anger,</hi> consider in these Particulars:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> In the common Scripture resemblances, 1. Its <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> compared to a <hi>fire:</hi> so in my <hi>Text, If his wrath be kindled:</hi> a <hi>fire</hi> so hot, that if it be kindled but <hi>a little, or as it were a little,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>blessed are all they</hi> &amp;c. His <hi>indignation</hi> is said▪ <hi>(Heb.</hi> 10. 27.) to be <hi>fiery:</hi> yea so much will he be in it, that he <hi>himself</hi> is said <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 24. Ezek. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. Isa 30. 10. Mat. 10. 28.</note> to be a <hi>fire,</hi> yea a <hi>consuming fire,</hi> Heb. 12 29. Nothing more dreadfull then <hi>fire,</hi> and no fire so dreadfull as the <hi>fire</hi> of the <hi>Sons wrath.</hi> For, 1. This <hi>fire</hi> burns <hi>spiritually,</hi> it destroyes the soul: other <hi>fire</hi> can but <hi>burn</hi> the <hi>body,</hi> and therefore (in comparison) is not to be feared. It scorcheth the conscience: Other fire burns the <hi>dross,</hi> this the <hi>gold.</hi> 2. It therefore burns much more <hi>painfully</hi> than materiall fire, 'tis of <hi>Gods</hi> own kindling, yea he <hi>himself</hi> is said to <hi>be</hi> this fire: no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell that the <hi>breath of the Lord</hi> should be called <hi>a stream of brimstone,</hi> Isa. 30 33. Its a <hi>fire</hi> not blown as ours, by mans <hi>breath,</hi> or any created <hi>blast,</hi> but by <hi>God</hi> himself, whose
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115037:19"/>
               <hi>breath</hi> is <hi>fire,</hi> and <hi>fewel,</hi> and <hi>bellows.</hi> It most exquisitely tormenteth, ordinary <hi>fire</hi> is but <hi>painted</hi> in comparison there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, 'tis <hi>pure</hi> perfect <hi>wrath:</hi> how unconceivably tormenting must needs be the pains inflicted by <hi>angry omnipotency!</hi> 3. It burns <hi>everlastingly,</hi> nor tears nor time can put it out. It eats not up what it <hi>burns,</hi> its over destroying, never destroyes, he that <hi>burns</hi> in it, shall never be burnt <hi>up</hi> in it: none an quench it, but he whom the sinner refuseth to quench it: That which makes other fire so <hi>dreadfull,</hi> namely to make an <hi>end</hi> of things, would make this fire <hi>mercifull.</hi> If he who cries <hi>fire▪ fire</hi> at midnight, at once both wakens and affrights us, with what amazement should they affect us, who know and denounce the <hi>terrors of the Lord!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Scripture-resemblance of this <hi>wrath</hi> is, the <hi>rage of a Bear rob'd of her whelps,</hi> Hos. 13. 8. whose naturall love to her whelps, whets her fury and strength against any whom she thinks stole them from her.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Consider the <hi>dreadfulness</hi> of this <hi>anger,</hi> in respect of the <hi>person</hi> who is thus angry, and so this anger must needs be unspeakable; he being not only 1. <hi>Infinitely wise,</hi> and so knowes <hi>what</hi> will vex his enemies, as also <hi>how</hi> to draw forth. every degree of <hi>force</hi> in any instrument, and how to <hi>apply</hi> it most fitly for torment: but likewise 2. <hi>All-powerfull,</hi> and so <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10 22. Ezek. 22. 14. Phil. 3. 21. Isa. 33. 14. Neh. 1. 6.</note> can <hi>set home</hi> every degree of force and vigour in the creature, <hi>either</hi> according to the strength of his <hi>own</hi> all-powerfull arm, and can <hi>create unconceivably greater torments than we can oppose or express: the force of Rocks, Mountains, Leviathans, is but weakness to his strength; they and all the world with all its force, are less than nothing.</hi> But also</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>soveraign</hi> Lord of Heaven and earth, who if he please can <hi>marshal</hi> all the forces of the creation into one body, and can Commissionate and impower for services of <hi>bloudiest revenge,</hi> not only his <hi>chief Officers,</hi> the Angels, but even his <hi>common souldiers</hi> the poorest creature and lowest worme. He it is that hath all sorts of <hi>woes</hi> and <hi>torments</hi> at his own command, and can <hi>appoint</hi> more of them by mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions than we ever heard of. 'Tis his <hi>anger</hi> that can make
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115037:20"/>
               <hi>offenders</hi> their own greatest <hi>afflicters</hi> and terors to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and <hi>transgressors</hi> to be their own <hi>tormentors,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustriously to fetch in <hi>matter</hi> of excessive horror to themselves out of their own bosoms, to <hi>gaze</hi> willingly in that <hi>false glass</hi> which Satan sets before them, and to be led by that <hi>lying cruelty</hi> which misrepresents to their affrighted imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, every <hi>gnat</hi> as a <hi>Camel,</hi> every <hi>mote</hi> as a <hi>molehill,</hi> every <hi>molehill</hi> as a <hi>mountain,</hi> every <hi>lustfull thought</hi> as a <hi>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domitical vilany,</hi> every <hi>idle word</hi> as a <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sperate blasphemy,</hi> every <hi>angry look</hi> as a <hi>bloudy murder,</hi> every transgression against <hi>ligdt of conscience</hi> as a sin against the <hi>holy Ghost.</hi> In this amazedness of <hi>spirit,</hi> God can cause a man to turn his own <hi>artillery,</hi> his wit and learning upon himself, to <hi>argue</hi> with (almost unanswerable) subtilty, against the pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness of his <hi>sins,</hi> to wound his wounds, with a <hi>conceit</hi> that they are incurable, to <hi>vex</hi> his very vexations with a refusing to be comforted. In a word, to turn to his own torment not only his <hi>crosses</hi> and tentations, but even the very <hi>comforts</hi> of his life, wife, children, gold, goods, preferments, as that <hi>wofull Spira</hi> did. And if God speak the <hi>word,</hi> the <hi>rebellious hand</hi> shall strike the <hi>head,</hi> the <hi>nails</hi> shall tear the <hi>skin,</hi> the <hi>teeth</hi> shall gnaw the <hi>flesh,</hi> and those who are made to take one anothers parts, shall become <hi>mutinous</hi> like the <hi>Midianites, who shea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed their swords in one anothers bowels;</hi> and all this to prove, that a man <hi>forsaken</hi> of God, hath least <hi>mercy</hi> for himself: and that <hi>he</hi> with whom God is <hi>angry,</hi> shall be to himself <hi>cruel.</hi> And as God can thus <hi>torment</hi> the conscience of the <hi>stoutest,</hi> so can he <hi>infatuate</hi> the counsels of his <hi>subtilest ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> and (in <hi>Ainsworths</hi> sense) can make <hi>Princes perish from the way,</hi> to wander and lose the right way, and not to know whither to go: yea he can cause them by their most poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick consultations, to <hi>consult shame to their houses,</hi> can give <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 10.</note>
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzar the heart of a beast;</hi> can make Princes <hi>to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the wilderness where there is no way,</hi> Psal. 107. 40. and can take <hi>away the understanding of the aged,</hi> Job 12. In short, this <hi>soveraign Lord</hi> hath all miseries at hand that may punish the outward man, he hath thousands of loathsome torturing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115037:20"/>
               <hi>diseases,</hi> which with a <hi>word</hi> he can send upon your <hi>bodies;</hi> upon your <hi>goods, houses, Navies, Armies flocks,</hi> he can send shours of <hi>fire and brimstone,</hi> and <hi>horrible tempests;</hi> upon your <hi>Names</hi> and all <hi>worldly grandeur,</hi> he can pour <hi>shamefull spewing,</hi> and so can <hi>stain the pride of all your glory;</hi> he can make a proud and puissant <hi>Bajazet,</hi> to be carried up and down in a <hi>wooden cage</hi> for a gazing stock: He can rouz up the <hi>fury</hi> that lurks and sleeps in your <hi>enemies</hi> breasts, and can turn your <hi>friends,</hi> your <hi>fellowers,</hi> your <hi>subjects</hi> against you, and <hi>cut you off</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your <hi>own doors,</hi> and spurn you about as <hi>dirt</hi> in the <hi>streets,</hi> and all this <hi>suddenly</hi> when you are at the <hi>highest,</hi> in your <hi>way,</hi> going on <hi>securely,</hi> and crying <hi>peace, peace▪</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>easily,</hi> with a <hi>word: Then shall be speak unto them in his wrath:</hi> ('tis but <hi>speaking</hi> and his enemies are undone:) with a <hi>breath,</hi> the <hi>breath of the Lord is a streams of brimstone:</hi> as if one who hath a <hi>plague-sore,</hi> should <hi>kill</hi> his enemies with but breathing on him; yea and <hi>irresistibly,</hi> when your friends <note place="margin">Lam. 1 9.</note> and forces are at the height of strength, even then (as 'tis said of <hi>Jerusalem) bringing you down wonderfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And lastly, Consider the <hi>dreadfulness</hi> of this <hi>anger,</hi> in regard of the <hi>persons with whom</hi> he is angry, and that both as they are <hi>weak,</hi> and so not able to resist him, and <hi>wicked,</hi> and so not fit to be spared <hi>by him:</hi> as they are <hi>wicked, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 9. 2. Hos. 13. 9.</note>
               <hi>for destruction,</hi> fitted <hi>fewel</hi> for the <hi>fire</hi> of vengeance, not as the <hi>green tree</hi> but the <hi>rottenstick,</hi> made combustible <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> by all sorts of aggravations of <hi>sinne</hi> committed against him, as a <hi>Creator,</hi> who <hi>made them</hi> of nothing; as a <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver</hi> who enjoynd them their <hi>duty;</hi> as a <hi>Judg</hi> who told them of his speedy and dreadfull coming to be <hi>averged</hi> of them; as a <hi>friend</hi> that woed and <hi>wept</hi> over them, and made them a fruitless <hi>tender</hi> of that <hi>occan of love,</hi> one drop whereof shall not be spared to eternity to cool their <hi>scorched</hi> tongue: how greatly must they provoke <hi>Christ</hi> a friend, who have chosen rather to be <hi>bruised</hi> under Satans feet, then to be <hi>lodgd</hi> in <hi>Christs</hi> bosome. 2. Consider them as weak <hi>dust and ashes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 64. 3. 41. 5.</note> and so no more able to resist him than the lightest <hi>chaff</hi> can a furious <hi>whirlwind,</hi> or the loosest <hi>straw</hi> can the most sweep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115037:21"/>
               <hi>torrent;</hi> The <hi>wax</hi> and <hi>stubble</hi> can more easily vanquish a violent <hi>flame,</hi> the tender <hi>cawl</hi> of the heart of a <hi>Lamb,</hi> can sooner overcome the <hi>paw</hi> and <hi>tooth</hi> of a rending and devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Bear,</hi> the most brittle <hi>earthen vessel</hi> sooner break in pieces an <hi>iron pillar,</hi> the casting up of a <hi>little pible,</hi> sooner repell the force of the greatest <hi>rock</hi> in its fall from Heaven, than can the enemies of <hi>Christ</hi> withstand the sury of his power, were they a world of <hi>Gyants,</hi> yea as many worlds of such as there are men in the world.</p>
            <p>This for the opening of the third and last particular in the <hi>Doctrinè, viz.</hi> the <hi>Argument</hi> by which Rulers are put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the duty of <hi>kissing the Son, lest he be angry:</hi> the <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <note place="margin">Application.</note> of the whole follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> I note, The <hi>tender and permanent care of Christ to</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>1</label>
               <hi>his Church.</hi> He requires the greatest Potentates to <hi>yeeld</hi> their <hi>subjection,</hi> for the promoting of <hi>subjection</hi> to <hi>him.</hi> Christ shews his care of the Church, by making some to be <hi>his</hi> subjects, who have power to relieve <hi>her.</hi> He requires that despised <hi>goodness,</hi> should be joyned with admired <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> that so it might have the more command and followers. 'Tis his goodness sometimes to make Religion on the <hi>Bench,</hi> discountenance wickedness at the <hi>Barr.</hi> When the <hi>governed Kiss the Son,</hi> they shall save themselves: but when <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors Kiss</hi> him, they may instrumentally save thousands. God sets and keeps up the <hi>pole</hi> of civill Dominion, that the weak <hi>Hop-bine</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> may be sustained. 'Tis promised, <hi>Psal.</hi> 22. 29. That <hi>the fat upon the earth shall whorship,</hi> i. e. That they who abound and flow with wealth, shall serve Christ. And <hi>Isa.</hi> 60. 3. That <hi>Kings shall come to the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Churches rising.</hi> &amp; 10. 11. <hi>That Kings shall minister to the Church.</hi> And <hi>Vers.</hi> 16. That <hi>she shall suck the breasts of Kings.</hi> And <hi>Isa.</hi> 49. 23. That <hi>Kings shall be nursing-Fathers, and Queens nursing-Mothers,</hi> to the Church, Infant-like for weakness; For <hi>Rulers</hi> to <hi>profess</hi> Christianity, and not to <hi>promote</hi> it, is not to <hi>Kiss the Son,</hi> unless by <hi>betraying</hi> him with a <hi>Kiss.</hi> Christs care to the Church, is so farre from taking away the <hi>Magistrats</hi> care,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115037:21"/> that it supposeth it. Your Dominion is given <hi>you</hi> to advance that of the chief <hi>Lord.</hi> The greatest <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>his</hi> vassals: And as they must give an account to an higher power <hi>hereafter,</hi> so should they serve for the promoting thereof for the <hi>present.</hi> In <hi>Isa.</hi> 60. 10, 11. where we read that Kings shall be <hi>brought,</hi> we read also, that they shall <hi>minister to the Church.</hi> Nor can they <hi>Kiss the Son,</hi> by <hi>ministring</hi> to the Church, if they <hi>Kiss</hi> and countenance her enemies. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Patriots,</hi> you that are our <hi>Rulers</hi> in this Parliament, 'tis often said, we live in Times wherein <hi>we may be as good as we please:</hi> wherein we enjoy in purity and plenty, the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Jesus Christ. Praised be God for this, even that God who hath delivered us from the imposition of prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Innovations, Altar-genu-flexions and cringings, with crossings, <hi>and all that popish trash and trumpery.</hi> And truly (I speak no more then what I have often thought and said) The removall of those insupportable burdens, countervails for the Blood and Treasure shed and spent in these late di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions. (Nor did I, as yet ever hear of any godly men that desired, were it possible, to purchase their friends or money again, at so dear a rate, as with the return of these, to have those soul-burdning, Antichristian yokes re-imposed upon us: And if any such there be, I am sure that desire is no part of their godliness, and I professe my self in that to be none of the number.) But though it be a mercy that we may be as good as we please, yet I beseech you, as you love your own souls, as you dread the anger of <hi>him,</hi> whose <hi>anger if kindled but a little, blessed are all they that put their trust in him,</hi> let not men be suffered to be as wicked as they please, let them not vent and print what errours they please, to the dishonour of the <hi>Son</hi> to whom you profess <hi>subjection.</hi> The first <hi>Table</hi> should be the Magistrates <hi>first</hi> care; and if they are injurious to all <hi>Christians,</hi> who take away but one of the <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> from us, certainly they are as injurious both to <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> who take away <hi>one Table</hi> from them, as they do who say the <hi>Magistrates</hi> have nothing to do in matters of Religion. You must keep both <hi>Tables</hi> not onely
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115037:22"/> as <hi>men,</hi> but also as <hi>Rulers.</hi> If you be the <hi>Shields of the earth,</hi> you must protect the <hi>glory</hi> of God; If you be <note place="margin">Psal. 47. 9. Ezek. 34. 2.</note>
               <hi>Shepherds,</hi> you must take care that the <hi>Flock</hi> of Christ wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not in the waies of hell without care to reduce them, that <hi>grievous Wolves,</hi> seducers have no liberty to devoure <hi>it,</hi> and that <hi>it</hi> be not put into poysonfull Pasture to feed in. 'Tis true, you are not to prepare their <hi>food,</hi> for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the <hi>Ministers:</hi> yet <hi>you</hi> must hinder those from feeding <hi>them,</hi> who give them <hi>poyson</hi> instead of <hi>food;</hi> as though <hi>you</hi> take not upon <hi>you</hi> the calling of <hi>Physicians,</hi> yet <hi>you</hi> must so farre regard the bodies of <hi>subjects,</hi> as to take care that <hi>Physicians</hi> prescribe not <hi>poyson</hi> to their <hi>Patients</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of wholesome <hi>Physick.</hi> Certainly <hi>you</hi> are not called <hi>Gods</hi> in the Scripture, that <hi>you</hi> should cast off all care of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness,</hi> and suffer all to be <hi>ungodly;</hi> God never appointed Magistrates to be <hi>Ox-herds</hi> (as many people make them) that is, onely to put the people as <hi>Oxen</hi> into good <hi>Pasture,</hi> and to give them store of <hi>feeding</hi> and <hi>pasture,</hi> but not to care who carries them to the <hi>Shambles,</hi> or who knocks them on the <hi>head;</hi> This is a pitifull Magistrate who doth thus, only provides peace and outward plenty for people, not regarding whether seducers draw them into <hi>soul damning</hi> heresies or no. Surely this <hi>Magistrate,</hi> though he may approve of our <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 2.</note> living a <hi>peaceable and quiet life</hi> under him, yet lives as if he would have the next words [in <hi>all godliness and honesty]</hi> blotted out of the <hi>Bible.</hi> If this latter must be the end of the subjects <hi>Prayers,</hi> it must likewise be the end of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrats <hi>Government.</hi> If it be the duty of a naturall Parent to bring up his Child in the <hi>fear and nurture of the Lord,</hi> Eph. 6. 4. Surely it is more the duty of a <hi>Politicall</hi> Parent to do so: Must the <hi>natural</hi> Parent take heed that his Child be kept from <hi>knives, poyson, fire,</hi> &amp;c. and may the <hi>political</hi> Parent suffer all his Children to be <hi>destroyed</hi> by <hi>damnable heresies,</hi> and by being brought up in the <hi>nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of the <hi>devill.</hi> I will never believe that; 'tis a Doctrine against all sense as well as Scripture. Are you to have parentall honour by vertue of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115037:22"/>
               <hi>fith Commandement,</hi> and are you not to perform paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall duties by vertue thereof? Never did I hear that those Rulers long preserved their <hi>own</hi> Names, who suffered <hi>Gods</hi> to be prophaned. And though possibly they may please the distempered appetites of some, yet certainly, they are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the spirituall <hi>health</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> and to their own tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eternall <hi>happiness.</hi> The <hi>fear</hi> of God is the best foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 17. Prov. 24. 21.</note> of <hi>obedience</hi> to Magistrates: Ungodly men will not conscienciously be <hi>good</hi> subjects. Men may from a principle of <hi>self-love,</hi> forbear the opposing of Magistracy, as a <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> but onely from a principle of <hi>conscience,</hi> can they abhor it as a sin. Humane Laws may make men <hi>hide,</hi> onely Gods Law can make men <hi>hate</hi> disobedience. The power of the <hi>Word</hi> in the consciences of people, binds more strongly to obedience, then the power of the <hi>Sword</hi> over the bodies of people. The way for the <hi>Magistrate</hi> to bring men under his <hi>subjection,</hi> is to his utmost to make them <hi>subjects</hi> to <hi>Christ.</hi> If Rulers provide for the keeping of Gods <hi>Laws,</hi> the <hi>observation</hi> of their own will follow of course.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I note, <hi>Magistracy is consistent with the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>2</label>
               <hi>of the Lord, and the kissing of the Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>Text</hi> indeed commands <hi>Kings and Judges</hi> to <hi>serve the one,</hi> and to <hi>Kiss the other:</hi> but neither it, nor any other Scripture saith, lay away your <hi>Crowns,</hi> and <hi>Scepters,</hi> throw away your <hi>Purple,</hi> and give over your <hi>Magistracy.</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, this <hi>Psalm</hi> was penned for Gospel-times, as <hi>Augustine</hi> tels us in his forty eighth <hi>Epistle,</hi> even for Times wherein the <hi>Son</hi> was to have the <hi>utmost parts of the earth for his possession,</hi> verse 8. And yet onely the <hi>regulating</hi> of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy, being here <hi>enjoyned,</hi> the <hi>establishing</hi> thereof is also here plainly <hi>impli'd.</hi> The <hi>Authour</hi> of this <hi>Psalm</hi> was no fifth-monachy-man, he endeavours to <hi>divert</hi> the <hi>stream</hi> of <note place="margin">Non eripit mortalia qui sceptra dat coelestia. <hi>Prud.</hi> Dan. 3. 12. Ezra 4. 13. Acts 17. 18.</note>
               <hi>Magistratical power</hi> into the right channel, but not to dry <hi>it</hi> up. God is not a God of <hi>order</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Author of confusion</hi> in the <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> nor do the Laws of Christ in the <hi>former</hi> bring in lawlesness into the <hi>later:</hi> One of his <hi>Ordinances</hi> doth not abolish another. Christs
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115037:23"/>
               <hi>Scepter</hi> swallowes not up (as did <hi>Arons</hi> rod the rods of the <hi>Aegyptions)</hi> the Scepters of earthly <hi>Monarchs,</hi> nor doth he who come to give <hi>heavenly,</hi> take away <hi>earthly Crowns.</hi> It hath been the constant endeavour of Satan to perswade <hi>civil Governours</hi> that Christs <hi>Kingdom</hi> is an enemy to theirs: but he who when he had a <hi>right,</hi> would not be made a <hi>King,</hi> gives no liberty to those who have none, to <hi>pull</hi> down those whom he hath set <hi>up.</hi> No, his <hi>example</hi> and <hi>precept</hi> teach private Christians the contrary, even to be subject to the <hi>higher powers,</hi> those which <hi>are by his providence,</hi> not onely those which <hi>ought to be by his precept,</hi> to inquire indeed into the nature of all <hi>Commands,</hi> not to dispute the <note n="*" place="margin">Solent pleri{que} inquitere ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lose quo quis{que} jure adeptus sit imperium, atqui hoc solo contentos esse decet quod vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus eos <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidere.</hi> Calv. <hi>in</hi> 1 Pte. 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Apostolus tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit frivolam hominum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riositatem, qui saepe solent in quirere quo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re adepti fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint imperium qui rerum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuntu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, satis autem nobis esse debet quod <hi>praes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt,</hi> nam manu Domini sunt impositi. <hi>Calv. in</hi> Ro. 13. Gerentibus <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> imperium debent se sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cere. Non est spectandum quo j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, vel quâ in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uriâ quis potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem invaserit, sed tantum si potestatem <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat.</hi> Bucer. <hi>in</hi> Rom. 13. Nihil refert <hi>qu modo</hi> perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ad officium▪ pervenerit, dum enim ibi <hi>est,</hi> certum est De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ibi illum collocasse. <hi>Olevian.</hi> in Rom. 13. Quaecun{que} potestas usum gladii, &amp; <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> habet im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perium, à Deo est. <hi>Mus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> in Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Non est sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorum de principis jure disputare, sed simpliciter <hi>prasent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistratibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedire. <hi>Gualt. in</hi> Rom. 13. Sic <hi>Petrus Martyr, Parae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes fere Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati.</note>
               <hi>titles</hi> of those which are <hi>Commanders:</hi> (and truely, were every private Christian to satisfie his <hi>conscience</hi> in the goodness of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours <hi>title</hi> before he yeelded <hi>obedience,</hi> I think it would be hard to determine, whether the <hi>condition</hi> of the <hi>Governor,</hi> or the <hi>conscience</hi> of the <hi>governed</hi> would be exposed to the greater misery.) Christ hath not so little care of his <hi>Church</hi> (as yet in <hi>her</hi> tender infant-age) as to leave <hi>her</hi> altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some indulgent and fostering friends, in whose <hi>bosome</hi> she may <hi>lodg,</hi> and whose <hi>breasts</hi> she may <hi>suck▪</hi> He sees not the World (as yet) so safe a <hi>place,</hi> as totally to deprive <hi>her</hi> of the <hi>protection</hi> of Princes. No, nor is he so regardless of the good of those who <hi>cry</hi> down <hi>Magistrates,</hi> as they are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. They who are weary of <hi>Magistrates,</hi> are weary of all the blessings and comforts of <hi>peace;</hi> and in labouring to pull down the <hi>Pillars,</hi> they strive to pull down the <hi>building</hi> on their own and others heads. What would <hi>Countries</hi> be without <hi>Government,</hi> but the <hi>dens</hi> of <hi>wild Beasts. Judah and Israel dwelt safely, every man under his Vine and Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree all the daies of Solomon,</hi> 1 King. 4. 25. <hi>Even Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar was a Tree whose fruit was meat for all, under which the Beasts of the field dwelt, and upon whose branches, the Fowles of the Heaven had their habitation,</hi> Dan. 4. 21. The <hi>Funerals</hi> of a <hi>political</hi> Parent, millions of Children will ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate with <hi>tears.</hi> Over <hi>Saul</hi> who was wicked and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, doth <hi>David</hi> bid <hi>the Daughters of Israel to weep, who</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115037:23"/>
               <hi>cloathed them with scarlet,</hi> 2 Sam. 1. 24. And when God threatens the taking away <hi>the staff of Bread,</hi> and <hi>the stay of water,</hi> he adds (as no less judgment) the taking away <hi>the Judge and the Prophet,</hi> the <hi>Prudent and the Ancient,</hi> Isa. 3. 1, 2. Dominion is the <hi>breath</hi> which so many thousands <hi>draw:</hi> Take it away, none can say this is mine. <hi>If the Magistrate were not a God to man, man would soon prove a Devil to man.</hi> Violent and bloody <hi>men</hi> fear not <hi>Hell,</hi> so much as the <hi>halter.</hi> Like beasts, they are more afraid of the <hi>flash</hi> of <hi>powder,</hi> then of the <hi>bullet:</hi> And though their fear of the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi> saves not their own <hi>souls,</hi> yet many times hath it saved our <hi>lives.</hi> Without Magistrates, <hi>robbery</hi> would be a Law, and men like Dogs, try all right by their <hi>teeth.</hi> Where there is no <hi>Ruler,</hi> any man may be a <hi>Tyrant.</hi> ('Tis just with God, that they should feel the curse of <hi>Anarchy,</hi> who were never thankfull for <hi>Magistracy)</hi> And if any Professors of <hi>Christianity</hi> be enemies to Magistrates, 'tis not because of <hi>Christianity,</hi> but because they are but Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of <hi>it.</hi> Though I suspect that the <hi>reason</hi> why they cry out against <hi>Government,</hi> is not because they would have no <hi>Government,</hi> but because they would have it in themselves, or else they desire to burn this <hi>rod,</hi> that they may play the <hi>wantons</hi> the more freely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I note, <hi>The greatest in the world are not allowed to be loose and lawless.</hi> Its not consistent with the <hi>soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the great King, to suffer any subject within his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>3</label> who will be absolute, and not <hi>yeeld</hi> him his <hi>homage,</hi> nor with his <hi>wisdom,</hi> to make any thing which he indends not to use. Superiority gives no dispensation for impiety: The <note place="margin">Qui se excipit se decipit. <hi>Bern. ad E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gen.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>greatest</hi> are not exempted from obedience to <hi>Christ.</hi> Here, what <hi>Bernard</hi> speaks in another case, is most true, <hi>He that exempts himself, deceives himself.</hi> The <hi>highest</hi> Potentate cannot be ungodly by <hi>Authority.</hi> The tallest <hi>Cedar,</hi> the stoutest <hi>Oak</hi> must bend or break. No <hi>eminency</hi> of <hi>place</hi> bears any out in <hi>sin.</hi> The <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Judgment-seat,</hi> gives Kings and Vassals an equality of <hi>condition,</hi> and the Scripture gives both an equal <hi>obligation</hi> to duty. Nor yet is <hi>Religon,</hi> any dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115037:24"/> to <hi>greatness,</hi> or diminution to <hi>Majesty.</hi> To serve Christ, is to raign; A Christian Ruler, is as thankfull, that Christ will deign to be his <hi>Master,</hi> as an heathen Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate is proud, that he can make many to be his <hi>servants. Theodosius</hi> esteemed this, the highest of all his Titles <note place="margin">Ultimus Christi seruus.</note> (Though an Emperour) <hi>the lowest servant of Christ.</hi> He who in his <hi>dignity</hi> serves not Christ, is at best but like a <hi>small</hi> letter in a <hi>great</hi> gay, where there is (though much <hi>flourish)</hi> yet little <hi>benefit,</hi> much hinderance to the Reader. Its more honour to serve <hi>him,</hi> then to have Emperours serve <hi>us.</hi> Indeed, all things serve <hi>him,</hi> that serves <hi>Christ.</hi> How needless, How unsuitable is it for <hi>great ones,</hi> to fear nothing more then to have a <hi>name</hi> to fear God? and of all things to be most ashamed of their <hi>glory!</hi> The desirable thing even in a Prince is <hi>godlinss.</hi> As soon as <hi>Angels</hi> ceased to be holy, they began to be Devils, though their other accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishments of <hi>strength, wisdom, spirituality,</hi> &amp;c. remained with them. The rarest endowments without <hi>grace,</hi> make none <hi>excellent,</hi> nor beside <hi>this</hi> will any thing have a luster at the <hi>last</hi> day: All <hi>created beauties</hi> will die, decay, and disappear, when the <hi>Son of righteousnes</hi> appeares. Holiness though <hi>veyled</hi> with the most <hi>contemptible</hi> outside, is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a silent <hi>Majesty:</hi> and sin even in the highest <hi>dignity,</hi> bewrayes a secret vileness. Sinne <hi>alone</hi> is the deflou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and deformity of the <hi>creature,</hi> the debasing, disennoble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and degrading of <hi>nature.</hi> How guilty even of a most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suitable <hi>condescension</hi> is it, for a Princes spirit to be <hi>inslav'd</hi> to sinne! The <hi>highest</hi> never go below themselves, but in sinning against <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I note, That <hi>they who refuse subjection to the Son,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>4</label>
               <hi>cannot be sheltred from destruction by their worldly greatness.</hi> The greatest Potentates if they will not <hi>Kiss the Son,</hi> must feel his wrath, and finde to their cost, that <hi>they</hi> are but <hi>weaklings.</hi> No strength upon earth can make an <hi>enemy</hi> to the <hi>Son of God,</hi> shot-proof against the Arrows of his <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</hi> As nothing can offend where is goodness will <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve,</hi> so nothing can defend where his justice will <hi>strike.</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115037:24"/> Though the <hi>high-towering pride</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of Princes may hold the earth in awe, yet they cannon threaten <hi>Heaven,</hi> but the closer they press to the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the nearer they lie to his <hi>lightning.</hi> If the heads of worldly <hi>Potentates,</hi> were raised to the <hi>Stars,</hi> rebellion against the <hi>Son of God,</hi> will bring them down into the <hi>dust.</hi> He can easily <hi>stain the pride of all their glory, and bring into contempt all the honourable of the earth,</hi> Isa. 23. 9. Soon shall they feel the weight of Christs <hi>power,</hi> and their own <hi>rebellions.</hi> Their's no evasion from, no fortification against the <hi>Lord.</hi> The strongest and the best fortified <hi>Castles,</hi> the most formidable <hi>preparations</hi> of <hi>war,</hi> the closest <hi>confederacies</hi> with the most potent <hi>allies,</hi> the fullest <hi>treasuries,</hi> the best furnished <hi>Armories,</hi> the proudest <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies,</hi> the most numerous and resolved <hi>Armies,</hi> are infinitly more unable to withstand the <hi>Son of God,</hi> then the <hi>flax</hi> is to resist the <hi>flames,</hi> or the <hi>chass</hi> and <hi>smoke</hi> to contend with the most boisterious <hi>whirlewind;</hi> all creature-defences against an incensed <hi>God,</hi> are but <hi>paper-towers,</hi> or childish <hi>Castles</hi> of <hi>Cards.</hi> What were the proudest <hi>walls</hi> and <hi>towers</hi> of <hi>Jerico,</hi> but the derisions of <hi>rams-horns?</hi> What that of <hi>Babel,</hi> but a <hi>monument</hi> of the madness of those who build it? <hi>The horse is a vain thing for safety,</hi> Psal. 33. 17. The hors-man as vain as his horse. <hi>Horse and rider were once thrown into the Sea,</hi> Exo. 15. <hi>The stout-hearted are spoiled, they have slept their sleep, and none of the men of war have found their hands,</hi> Psal. 76. 5. In the day of his wrath the <hi>Lord will strike through Kings,</hi> Psal. 110. 5. And if the <hi>strength</hi> of Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates cannot deliver them, how should their <hi>weakness?</hi> If their <hi>Armour</hi> cannot save them, how should their <hi>nakedness?</hi> If their warlike <hi>puissance</hi> cannot <hi>preserve</hi> them, how should their <hi>dissembling,</hi> their <hi>perjury,</hi> their <hi>oppression,</hi> their <hi>lukewarmness,</hi> cursed <hi>neutrality</hi> in the cause of God, and all such impolitick <hi>policies?</hi> They who would shun <hi>wrath</hi> by any other meanes then by <hi>Kissing the Son,</hi> take mistaken courses. That <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill</hi> thought themselves doubtless very wise, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 48. who thought to prevent their destruction from the <hi>Romanes,</hi> by <hi>killing the Son,</hi> but that very policy which thy expected
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115037:25"/> should preserve them, proved the loss of their <hi>Nation,</hi> and its destruction by the <hi>Romanes.</hi> That Prince onely sets up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self upon a solid <hi>foundation,</hi> who sets up <hi>Christ</hi> above himself, and advanceth the <hi>Sons interest</hi> by and beyond his own, who makes the <hi>Son</hi> his <hi>friend,</hi> and sets himself against his own and peoples sinnes, the <hi>Sons</hi> enemies. And if this counsell will not be taken, then let the despisers thereof, though <hi>crowned, sceptered, adorned, adored</hi> Monarchs know, 'tis not because the <hi>Sons</hi> wrath is not <hi>terrible,</hi> but because they are <hi>insensible.</hi> If they will needs contend, some fellow-worm would be their fitter match. The <hi>Sons</hi> wrath is infinitly disproportionable to such an inconsiderable part of a <hi>dust,</hi> a <hi>drop,</hi> or of that which is <hi>less then nothing and vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I note, That <hi>they are the best friends to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>5</label>
               <hi>who by admonishing them of their duty of kissing the Son, endeavour to prevent their feeling of the Sons wrath.</hi> I know the nearness is so great between pride and principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that faithfull admonishers can hardly oppose the <hi>former,</hi> but they are counted enemies to the <hi>latter.</hi> And though plain dealing by reproofs be a <hi>Jewel,</hi> yet he who useth it, <note place="margin">Quid est pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum, nisi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivare in se odium totius mundi &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferni. <hi>Luther.</hi> Odium Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelii genius. <hi>Id.</hi>
               </note> doth instead of humbling the <hi>reproved,</hi> commonly harm the <hi>reprover:</hi> and that the most <hi>compendious</hi> way to derive upon a man the hatred of the Sons of men, is to plead for subjection to the <hi>Son of God.</hi> Not onely did a wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> call plain dealing <hi>Elijah,</hi> a <hi>troubler of Israel,</hi> but even good <hi>Asa was wroth with the seer.</hi> Truth, the more wholesome and pure it is, commonly the less toothsome and pleasing it is. And the thankfull receiving of <hi>holy</hi> reprehension, is a <hi>noble</hi> though a <hi>bloodness Martyrdom.</hi> And certainly till Satan lays down his hatred to <hi>Christ,</hi> and love to <hi>himself,</hi> he will never be in love with them who advance <hi>Christ,</hi> and oppose <hi>him;</hi> But grant all this, the <hi>servants</hi> of Christ must more study <hi>duty,</hi> then <hi>safety.</hi> And they can better endure the wrath of the Sons of men, for <hi>discharging,</hi> then the wrath of the <hi>Son of God</hi> for <hi>neglecting</hi> their duty. That Spirit by which they ought to be acted, had as well the shape of <hi>fiery tongues,</hi> as that of a <hi>Dove.</hi> They must not study to shew a <hi>smooth,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115037:25"/> but a <hi>safe</hi> way: not to prepare <hi>sauce,</hi> but <hi>Physick,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it's better, as <hi>Augustin</hi> well expresseth it, <hi>To love with severity, then to deceive with lenity.</hi> What evil have <hi>Magistrats</hi> above all other men deserved, that they should be destructively soothed, when a poor man shall be savingly admonished? I confess, <hi>reprehensions</hi> ought not to degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into <hi>sedition.</hi> The dignity of a Magistrates <hi>Office,</hi> ought not to suffer for the vices of his <hi>person:</hi> But yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther must sinfull flattery abolish love to the souls of those who are <hi>great,</hi> or zeal for him who is the <hi>greatest.</hi> In short, Even <hi>sincere reproofes,</hi> which tend to prevent the <hi>wrath of the great God,</hi> are not onely excusable, but commendable. 'Tis an holy <hi>impudence,</hi> to be <hi>impudent</hi> in urging any to take heed of <hi>damnation.</hi> It's a sinfull <hi>bashfulness▪</hi> to be so conrteous as to forget <hi>Christianity.</hi> We can never <hi>warn</hi> too much of <hi>eternall danger.</hi> It's very good manners to stay, and <hi>knock</hi> again, though we have <hi>knockt</hi> more then <hi>thrice</hi> at the <hi>door</hi> of a great mans <hi>conscience.</hi> Either <hi>here</hi> or <hi>hereafter,</hi> his <hi>conscience</hi> will commend <hi>us,</hi> though now his <hi>lusts</hi> be angry with <hi>us.</hi> If importunity overcame an unrighteous <hi>Judg</hi> to <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 5.</note> do good to another, how much more should it prevaile with him to do good for himself?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> I note, <hi>Rulers who upon their refusall of subjection to Christ, have felt the smart of his severe dispensations,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>6</label>
               <hi>should justifie him, and condemn themselves.</hi> When he puls them <hi>down,</hi> or plucks them <hi>out,</hi> laies their <hi>honour in the dust,</hi> and makes them as the 70 Kings, whose <hi>thumbes and great toes</hi> being cut off by <hi>Adonibezek,</hi> they were by loss of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer made unfit for <hi>fight,</hi> and by the loss of the latter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for <hi>flight:</hi> Or as <hi>Samson</hi> when his hair was cut off, even as <hi>other men:</hi> let them consider whether they have not cut <hi>off</hi> their <hi>lock of loyalty</hi> to the Lord Jesus. We need not go far for <hi>Instances</hi> of divine <hi>severity</hi> against great <hi>ones.</hi> How <note place="margin">Isa. 14. 16.</note> low and contemptible hath he laid those who <hi>have made the earth to tremble</hi> (as <hi>Isaiah)</hi> and have been (as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> speaks) <note place="margin">Ezek. 32. 27.</note>
               <hi>the terrour of the mighty in the Land of the living!</hi> Was it not the <hi>exalting</hi> himself against God that overthrew <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115037:26"/> that drove <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> out of his Kingdom among the <hi>beasts,</hi> that brought <hi>Manasseh</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah</hi> into <hi>Babiloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> fetters, that made <hi>Jehoiakim buried with the buriall of an</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 22. 18, 19.</note>
               <hi>Asse (none saying, ah his glory!) Drawn and cast forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the gates of Jerusalem,</hi> that <hi>made Coniah a despised broken Idol, a vessel wherein is no pleasure, and cast into a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 22. 28.</note>
               <hi>Land which he knew not.</hi> Is it any <hi>wonder,</hi> if they will let as many be Christs enemies as please, that he should retaliate in hindering none from being theirs? When the Lord deals thus with <hi>Rulers,</hi> they should look beyond a sturdy head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strong <hi>people.</hi> They have <hi>negotium cum Deo</hi> (as <hi>Calvin</hi> speaks) <hi>To do with God, who</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> speaks) <hi>Job.</hi> 12. 18. <hi>loseth the bond</hi> or belt <hi>of Kings,</hi> degrading them of their <hi>dignity,</hi> both <hi>regal</hi> and <hi>military,</hi> and <hi>girdeth their loyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 17. 7, 8.</note>
               <hi>with a girdle,</hi> as <hi>servants</hi> were wont to be girded in the: attendance upon their <hi>Masters,</hi> for greater readiness: so that from <hi>Commanders,</hi> they are turned into <hi>servants,</hi> and made (as <hi>Solomon</hi> speaks <hi>Ecl.</hi> 10 7.) <hi>to walk as servants on the earth.</hi> Into this <hi>condition</hi> (I say) when God brings <hi>great ones,</hi> their work is to look inward, and upward, and to <hi>study</hi> what their <hi>sin</hi> hath been, which hath provoked God to <hi>debase</hi> that which he commands all other to <hi>honour.</hi> When their <hi>subjects</hi> cast off the <hi>yoke</hi> of obedience to them, let them consider whether they have not denied <hi>homage and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Son of God,</hi> and whether it be not for their <hi>despising of God,</hi> that now they are so <hi>lightly esteemed</hi> among men. If it be the Lord who <hi>subdues</hi> the people under Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as <hi>David</hi> speaks, <hi>Psal.</hi> 18. 47.) doubtless 'tis he who <hi>subdues</hi> them <hi>under</hi> their people. And if at any time they be born down with the <hi>floods</hi> of popular <hi>tumults,</hi> by Gods breaking the <hi>banks</hi> and <hi>bounds</hi> of his wonted <hi>protection</hi> about them, let them <hi>examine</hi> themselves, whether they have not <hi>transgressed</hi> the <hi>bounds</hi> of Gods <hi>Commandements;</hi> and the putting of <hi>proud Princes</hi> upon an <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>humble conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 17.</note> hereof, is one main <hi>end</hi> of such severe <hi>dispensations of Providence,</hi> shewn in their debasement. As for those whose <hi>worldly greatness</hi> and <hi>power</hi> is still continued, in their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115037:26"/> of rebellion against <hi>Christ,</hi> they must know that these are but angry <hi>smiles</hi> in the face of God. God <hi>holds his peace,</hi> but <note place="margin">Ultrix miseri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia.</note> he is not <hi>dumb;</hi> he <hi>winks,</hi> but he is not <hi>blind.</hi> The abused <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of the Son, wiat length be turned into <hi>burning fury,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, yeall, by and proportionably to his <hi>forbearance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seaventhly, <hi>How easily can the wrath of the Son reach in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors and those of low degree who continue in rebellion against</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>7</label>
               <hi>him?</hi> If he smites Princes, he will not alway, nor is it for want of power, if for the present he doth spare mean peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Yea commonly <hi>people</hi> are deep sharers both in the punishment, and in the provocations of <hi>Princes.</hi> How should we in a lower rank, humble our selves before this <hi>great God!</hi> The low shrub may be stubd up or crusht, if the tall Cedar be cut down: Certainly God will not endure a <hi>proud heart</hi> in those of a <hi>low condition.</hi> And truly the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son oft, why <hi>men of low degree</hi> are not as notorious <hi>opposers</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> as are proud Potentates, is not for want of <hi>poyson</hi> but of <hi>power.</hi> A little <hi>thimble</hi> may be as full as the largest <hi>vessell,</hi> though it cannot hold so much. According to his <hi>measure,</hi> a private person may be as wicked as the most des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>enemy</hi> that ever Christ had among the worst of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> 'Tis therefore the duty of subjects who observe the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Judgments</hi> of God upon Princes, at <hi>once</hi> to tremble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and to take heed of <hi>sin. Tutors</hi> usually correct young <hi>Princes</hi> for their faults, by correcting the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Plebeians</hi> in their presence, their <hi>Governours</hi> putting them in fear by the <hi>smart</hi> which others feel; How should common people then <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>mend</hi> when God <hi>corrects</hi> the <hi>greatest</hi> Monarchs in their sight, for their <hi>warning!</hi> How happy <hi>we,</hi> and how cheap our <hi>schooling,</hi> to have all our Learning at the <hi>cost</hi> of another! Princes in their wickedness, are too often examples of <hi>imitation;</hi> but it would be our greater <hi>wisdom,</hi> to make them in their woes, examples of <hi>Caution.</hi> They who are not warned by the <hi>miseries</hi> of others (especially <hi>great ones)</hi> cannot sin at a cheap <hi>rate.</hi> They who sin against such <hi>examples,</hi> sin <hi>presumptuously.</hi> How just is God in hitting <hi>those</hi> to whom he had said before, <hi>stand off!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115037:27"/>
            <p> To conclude with some suitable <hi>Considerations</hi> to engage <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋse </seg>last.</label> you to this your duty of <hi>Kissing the Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Study the brittleness of all worldly greatness;</hi> how unable it is to endure the shock of the <hi>Sons fury!</hi> how easily he can dissolve and dissipate it! A little prick with a <hi>pin</hi> lets all the wind out of the most swolne bladder; and if the <hi>Son</hi> do but touch you, speak to, yea, breath or look upon you in <hi>wrath,</hi> all your greatness vanisheth: <hi>men of high degree are vanity</hi> to all that trust in them, and their height and strength shall prove in the day of the <hi>Sons wrath</hi> but vanity and a lye to themselves, if they confide therein. <hi>Riches profit not in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Prov. 11. 4.</note>
               <hi>day of wrath. Make not lies your refuge.</hi> The greatest is but <hi>soul</hi> and <hi>soyl,</hi> the one a puff of <hi>wind,</hi> the other a pile of <hi>dust,</hi> made of the same mettall that the meanest are, and <hi>their flesh (Neh.</hi> 5. 5.) the same with theirs; the greatest Judges on earth are but earthen Judges, frail <hi>sons of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Study the end of the Sons advancing of you.</hi> You were never set up by him to <hi>suffer</hi> him to be low, much less to <hi>make</hi> him so, this was never the <hi>end</hi> of your being <hi>men, Christians</hi> or <hi>Magistrates:</hi> Say as <hi>Mordecai</hi> to the (at first) <note place="margin">In maximâ fortunâ mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma est licentia.</note> timorous <hi>Esther, Who knows whether we are come to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for such a time as this?</hi> If you do not more for <hi>Christ</hi> than those who have no power at all in their hands, you are therefore <hi>worse</hi> than they, because you are not <hi>better,</hi> and do therefore <hi>less</hi> because you do not <hi>more: To whomsoever much is given, of him shall much be required,</hi> Luk. 12. 48. What more equall than that you should honour him again, when he honoureth you, whom you stand bound to honour, whether he thus honour you or no? And consider whether there be any <hi>worth</hi> in any honour of the world, but only that thereby <hi>Christ</hi> may be advanced.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Labour for faith in threatnings:</hi> restrain not belief only to what God hath promised: let faith overcome all <note place="margin">Jer. 17. 10. Heb. 11. Jona 5. 5.</note>
               <hi>probabilities</hi> that seem to keep away <hi>judgment,</hi> as well as those that seem to keep away <hi>mercy:</hi> Faith will <hi>teach</hi> to fear, and fear will <hi>prevent</hi> feeling. 'Tis the nature of faith to <hi>apply</hi> a threatned plague, as 'tis the nature of sense to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115037:27"/>
               <hi>mourn</hi> under an inflicted punishment. When God threatens <hi>wrath,</hi> say not in security, 'tis the <hi>shadow of the mountnais, the vision fayleth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Yeeld subjection to the Son for himself:</hi> let it not be swaid by interest. The most (like the <hi>Roman,</hi> who being commanded to bow before that <hi>Persian,</hi> stoopt indeed, but 'twas only to take up his Ring) in their seeming respects to <hi>Christ,</hi> do indeed really but adore their own designs. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is therefore so ill-shaped in most Princes Dominions, because 'tis cast into the mould of <hi>interest.</hi> Let not the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Christ be the <hi>scaffold,</hi> and serving your selves the <hi>building,</hi> regard Christ as the <hi>scope,</hi> not in a way of <hi>subser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viency</hi> to something else: bow down to his <hi>person</hi> not to his <hi>cloathes:</hi> Let subjection to him be its own wages: let <hi>Christ</hi> be sweet for himself. How unworthy is it for policy and base <hi>self,</hi> to commensurate and subordinate our respects to the Son of God! and to make the Son of God, not to <hi>hold,</hi> but to <hi>be</hi> a stirrup to carnal interest.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Look on Christ the right way:</hi> see him in his spirituall <hi>glory,</hi> let the eye of <hi>faith</hi> pierce through the contemptible outside of all his <hi>appointments,</hi> and followers. Take not the worlds report concerning <hi>him; he hath no enemy, but the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</hi> Christ was never appointed to gratify <hi>sense,</hi> but onely to relieve <hi>faith.</hi> A skilfull <hi>eye</hi> contemns the gaudry of all that workmanship which is onely <hi>rich,</hi> and hath nothing of <hi>Art,</hi> but admires the excellency of a <hi>Picture</hi> curiously <hi>drawn,</hi> though it be not adorned with <hi>gold,</hi> but set in a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>frame.</hi> Look upon <hi>Christ</hi> onely, as that truly <hi>excellent Object,</hi> and on all the <hi>beauties</hi> of the world, as <hi>fictitious</hi> and in <hi>appearance</hi> onely. Behold Christ as the <hi>Word</hi> discovers, and as <hi>Faith</hi> discerns <hi>him,</hi> in regard both of what he <hi>is,</hi> and <hi>doth,</hi> and that both for encourragment to his <hi>subjects,</hi> and affrightment of <hi>rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Study the happiness of subjection to the Son. First,</hi> In the <hi>honourableness</hi> thereof. The meanest subject of Christ is a <hi>King, Rev.</hi> 16. A fellow <hi>servant</hi> with the glorious <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> and put upon honourable <hi>imployments,</hi> the <hi>saving of</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115037:28"/>
               <hi>souls,</hi> the <hi>conversing with God, subduing of Principalities.</hi> The greatest honour of <hi>Angels,</hi> is to be Christs <hi>Messengers.</hi> Christ yoke is onely <hi>beauty,</hi> not burden to the <hi>neck.</hi> The service of <hi>sin</hi> is the onely debasement of the souls <hi>excellency,</hi> even the <hi>service</hi> of what is unspeakably below what ever hath a being, and is that wherein it's onely possible for a man to go truely below <hi>himself. Secondly,</hi> In its <hi>sweetness</hi> and pleasantness. <hi>Christs</hi> subjects have a <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>gracious Prince, Rev.</hi> 9. 9. Who never gives a <hi>Law</hi> that's <hi>grievous,</hi> who never commands a <hi>duty,</hi> but he gives <hi>strength,</hi> never enjoyns a <hi>work,</hi> but he gives an <hi>hand,</hi> never sends on an <hi>errand,</hi> but he gives a <hi>tongue,</hi> never imposes a <hi>burden,</hi> but he gives a <hi>back:</hi> in one word, never is our <hi>Master,</hi> but he is likewise our <hi>fellow-worker:</hi> Yea, so sweet is subjection to <hi>him,</hi> that his subjects count it more of <hi>priviledge</hi> then <hi>task,</hi> and would think their lives <hi>bitter</hi> without <hi>it. Subjection</hi> to Christ is bitter to nothing, but to that, which he will also destroy, or else it will destroy us, namely <hi>sin. Great peace have they who keep his Laws.</hi> Were there no <hi>Heaven</hi> to be expected hereafter, this <hi>peace</hi> would much more then <note place="margin">Psal. 119.</note> countervaile for all outward troubles that accompany it. Subjection to <hi>sin,</hi> is cruelty to <hi>conscience</hi> and <hi>carcass.</hi> How many <hi>wounds</hi> and <hi>woes</hi> endures a sinner, to get to those that are <hi>eternall!</hi> Oh the gripes and wounds of <hi>conscience,</hi> the <hi>heart-</hi>vexations of the most gaudy <hi>sinner,</hi> even when he is in his holy-day cloathes! Like a <hi>Book</hi> well bound, but full of <hi>Tragedies,</hi> within he is full of silent scourges, and soul-smart. A <hi>vassal</hi> to sin, like the <hi>Roman</hi> slave who had his <hi>thumbs</hi> cut off, that so he might be able to handle the <hi>Oar,</hi> but not the <hi>Sword,</hi> is onely left in a posture of activity in his sins drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery. How many lashes doth <hi>Satan</hi> give his <hi>slaves,</hi> to drive them with speed to their own <hi>ruine,</hi> even as the cruel driver whips his pack-laden <hi>Jade</hi> through every miery slough! And yet <hi>lust</hi> is here a wicked mans <hi>God</hi> (sure 'twill hereafter be his <hi>Devill)</hi> But <hi>Thirdly, View subjection to Christ</hi> in its <hi>gainfulness</hi> and <hi>advantage.</hi> He withholds from his <hi>subjects</hi> nothing but clogs, snares, and hinderances from <hi>happiness:</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115037:28"/> Christ gives as more <hi>for</hi> them, so more <hi>to</hi> them then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Prince;</hi> the rewards he gives them on this side <hi>Heaven</hi> are unspeakable. In the very <hi>keeping</hi> of his <hi>Commands,</hi> there is <hi>great reward.</hi> Their <hi>work</hi> seems to have more of <hi>wages</hi> then <hi>work,;</hi> those <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, those sweet <hi>intimations</hi> and <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasts</hi> of Heaven, how ravishingly delightfull are <hi>they!</hi> But how <hi>great</hi> then is <hi>their reward in Heaven!</hi> Their <hi>Joy</hi> there, is not so much said to enter <hi>into them,</hi> as they <hi>into it;</hi> and <note place="margin">Mat. 25. Psal. 16.</note> no marvell, 'tis the <hi>joy of their Lord,</hi> in whose presence is <hi>fulness of joy.</hi> Study, but yet expect not to understand the comfort and condescension of that <hi>Promise,</hi> Luk. 12. 37. to the subjects of Christ. <hi>He shall gird himself, and make them sit down to meat, and come forth and serve them.</hi> The <hi>Son</hi> of God serve them! Their <hi>dignity</hi> will not be less then their <hi>delight,</hi> if Majesty it <hi>self</hi> gives attendance at their <hi>Table:</hi> Nor yet will their <hi>delight</hi> be less then their <hi>dignity;</hi> For doubtles their <hi>chear</hi> and their <hi>attendance</hi> are both <hi>one.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in <hi>Heaven</hi> there shall be as many <hi>Kings</hi> as <hi>Subjects.</hi> To <hi>Kiss</hi> Thee (dear Lord) is to <hi>Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>